<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the supreme authority the Parliament of the Common-wealth of England, his excellency the Lord General Cromwell, and his Councell of Officers the humble remonstrance of Sir John Stawell, setting forth the reason of his first engaging on the late Kings part, and his deportment therein. His desisting from further action upon the Articles of Exeter. The benefit which he claimes by vertue of the said articles. The meanes by which that benefit hath been retarded. His several tryals, both by indictment at Common Law and in the High Court of Justice, for high treason, murder, and other felonies in relation to actions committed in the late unhappy warre; and his almost seven yeares imprisonment. The sequestration of his estate, and sale of the greatest part thereof. The proceedings and judgement of the Honourable Court of Articles thereupon: and his present state and condition.</title>
            <author>Stawell, John, Sir, 1599-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 226 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93839</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5351</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1072_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208213</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867182</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867182</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119479</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93839)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119479)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 160:E1072[2], 249:E1072[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the supreme authority the Parliament of the Common-wealth of England, his excellency the Lord General Cromwell, and his Councell of Officers the humble remonstrance of Sir John Stawell, setting forth the reason of his first engaging on the late Kings part, and his deportment therein. His desisting from further action upon the Articles of Exeter. The benefit which he claimes by vertue of the said articles. The meanes by which that benefit hath been retarded. His several tryals, both by indictment at Common Law and in the High Court of Justice, for high treason, murder, and other felonies in relation to actions committed in the late unhappy warre; and his almost seven yeares imprisonment. The sequestration of his estate, and sale of the greatest part thereof. The proceedings and judgement of the Honourable Court of Articles thereupon: and his present state and condition.</title>
                  <author>Stawell, John, Sir, 1599-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 76 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. for Henry Twyford,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]¹ B-G²  (g)¹ H-U² .</note>
                  <note>The words "setting forth .. and his present state and condition" are bracketed together on the title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stawell, John, --  Sir, 1599-1662 --  Trials, litigation, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Estates (Law) --  Cases --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Confiscations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119479:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TO THE SUPREME AUTHORITY THE Parliament of the Common-wealth of ENGLAND, His <hi>Excellency</hi> the LORD GENERAL CROMWELL, And his Councell of OFFICERS: THE HUMBLE REMONSTRANCE OF Sir <hi>JOHN STAWELL,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Setting forth
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Reaſon of his firſt engaging on the late KINGS Part, and his deportment therein.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>His deſiſting from further action upon the Articles of</hi> Exeter.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Benefit which he claimes by vertue of the ſaid Articles.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The meanes by which that Benefit hath been retarded.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>His ſeveral Tryals, both by Indictment at Common Law and in the High Court of Juſtice, for high Treaſon, Murder, and other Felonies in relation to actions com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the late unhappy Warre;</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>And his almoſt ſeven yeares Impriſonment.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Sequeſtration of his Eſtate, and ſale of the greateſt part thereof.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Proceedings and Judgement of the Honourable Court of Articles thereupon:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>And his preſent State and Condition.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T.R.</hi> for <hi>Henry Twyſord,</hi> Anno Dom. 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119479:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119479:2"/>
            <head>The humble REMONSTRANCE of Sir JOHN STAWELL.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was but of late that by the bleſſing of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, and your exceeding great Juſtice and favour, I was freed from ſome of thoſe many afflictions and calamities which attend a ſad condition, into which the practiſe, misinfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, and ill-grounded apprehenſions of ſome men, had throwne me; And that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to look back upon my miſeries already paſt, with that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment and ſecurity, which men enjoy in viewing Rocks, and raging Seas, when they themſelves are ſafe in Harbour, deſiring nothing more then to ſpend the reſidue of my dayes (which by natures proſcription cannot be many) in ſuch peaceable obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to this Commonwealth, as by your Faith and Honour made good unto me, I hold my ſelfe obliged unto: But now finding, that the reſtleſſe proceedings of ſuch as hate me without a cauſe, doe tend to nothing leſſe, then to reduce me to my former miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition, and conſequently to ruine both me and my po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; I have preſumed in all humility, and I hope free from offence, To declare and remonſtrate this my Caſe, to the end, That as my duty to heaven bindes me, I may evidence unto the world, Gods moſt remarkable mercies towards me, vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate your Honour and Juſtice, and undeceive the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whoſe Faith likewiſe is moſt highly concerned in theſe my ſufferings: And in ſo doing I will fix my ſelfe upon that truth which ſhall be avowed upon the faith of a Chriſtian, and honour of a Gentleman. And becauſe my undertaking under the late King have had the ill luck to be ſtained and aſperſed with too much forwardneſſe, as acting beyond the moderate and ſober limitations of a contrariant; and as if my nature had prompted me to the delight of cruelty in thoſe imployments: I ſhall begge your patience in ſuffering truth to be fetcht from its Fountaine, and hence to derive it to my preſent ſtate and condition.</p>
            <p>In the yeare 1640. by vertue of the late Kings writ of ſummons, I was choſen by the County of <hi>Somerſet</hi> one of the Knights to ſit in Parliament, and did accordingly attend that ſervice for the ſpace of eighteen moneths or thereabouts, at which time ſome
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119479:3"/>unhappy differences ariſing betwixt the late King and the two Houſes, I did receive ſignification of his pleaſure by a Letter (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected) from <hi>Beverley,</hi> and ſealed with his privy Signet, which followeth in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>CHARLES REX.</signed>
                     <salute>TRuſty and welbeloved, we greet you well.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Whereas we have iſſued forth our Commiſſion of Array for the County of <hi>Somerſet</hi> under our great Seal of <hi>England</hi> unto our right truſty and right entirely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved couſin and councellor, the Marquis <hi>Hertford,</hi> And with him have named you a Commiſſioner, In the execution whereof (and ſuch other publike ſervices as we have and ſhall intruſt unto you, your preſence, care, and utmoſt circumſpection is moſt neceſſary. We doe therefore hereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire you with all convenient ſpeed to repaire unto the ſaid County, and to attend that ſervice, wherein we doubt not you will ſo demeane your ſelfe as may be ſutable to the good opinion we have of you, and as may moſt promote the due execution ef this Commiſſion. Which at this time is of ſo high a conſequence, not onely to the ſecurity of our ſaid County, but to the peace of this Kingdome in generall. And becauſe this Commiſſion (by ſuch who declare all things illegall which ſuit not with their deſires or deſignes) is declared to be contrary to the Lawes, and thereupon you may be ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by one or both Houſes of Parliament as a Delinquent, for the execution thereof. We require you upon your alleageance not to intermit or in any ſort to neglect our ſaid ſervice upon any ſuch ſummons, by going on remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to <hi>London</hi> or any other place, ſave to us, or where it is fit for you to be in the proſecution of our ſaid ſervice, and ſuch further command as you ſhall receive under our own hand. And we doe hereby require and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all Sheriffes, Majors, Juſtices, Officers, Miniſters, and loving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects whatſoever, not onely to be aſſiſting and ayding unto you in caſe of need in your free paſſage from place to place. But alſo that they preſume not to attach your perſon, or ſerve you with any warrant, Order, or ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons whereunto we have not conſented, nor deteine or ſeize any of your goods or ſervants, or any thing to you belonging without our ſpeciall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe firſt obtained, as they and every of them will anſwer the contrary at their utmoſt perills. For which this ſhall be to you and them ſufficient war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and authority.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given at our Court at <hi>Beverley</hi> 
                        <date>the eleaventh day of <hi>July,</hi> in the eighteenth yeare of our Raigne.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>To our truſty and welbeloved Sir <hi>John Stawell, Knight of the</hi> Bath.</trailer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Command cauſed me within few dayes after to repaire to my houſe in the Country, where I received another Letter dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted unto me from the Lord Marquis <hi>Hertford</hi> dated at <hi>Bath,</hi> who was then Lord Lieutenant of that County, and recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the late King by the Houſe of Commons as a fit perſon for that command, and was as followeth.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119479:3"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I <hi>Am come by command from his Majeſty, with Commiſſion to muſter the Forces of this County, of which Commiſſion you are one: I intend to be on Wedneſday next at</hi> Wells, <hi>where I ſhall deſire your preſence, that I may impart the Commiſſion unto you, and adviſe further about the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution thereof. In the moan time I reſt,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your aſſured friend and Servant: HERTFORD.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Bath</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>July</hi> 24. 1642.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Upon this Summons I waited upon my Lord Marquis at <hi>Wells,</hi> together with two of my Sons, and ſome ſervants: And my Lord ſhewing me his Commiſſion, in which I found my ſelfe together with divers other perſons of honour and quality named Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, (which Commiſſion was produced and read in the high Court of Juſtice upon my Tryall) And in few dayes after, and before my removall from <hi>Wells,</hi> his Lordſhip had notice that ſome parts of that Country had put themſelves in Armes, and were mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching towards him, without his order, or any knowledge of their deſigne, whereupon it was concluded, that ſome of the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, namely, the now Lord <hi>Paulet,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Digby,</hi> Sir <hi>Francis Hauley,</hi> Mr. <hi>Windham</hi> and my ſelfe, who were beſt acquainted with the Country, ſhould with ſome horſe move towards them, upon which we went from <hi>Wells,</hi> and not farre from thence, we had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence that ſome of the Trained Bands of the Country were in a body under the command of Captaine <hi>Preston,</hi> comming to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a place called <hi>Marſhalls Elme;</hi> whereupon we went towards them, and when we came within view of them, after ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation amongſt our ſelves, we thought it fit to deal friendly and civilly with our Neighbours and Country-men, and that our good inclination to preſerve the peace of the Country might the better appeare, we ſent a Gentleman unto them to pray a capitulation and Parley; leſt that upon diſlikes grounded upon miſappre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, we might unhappily come to blowes: Hereupon foure of the Commiſſioners, of whom I was one, met with Mr. <hi>Pine,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sandys,</hi> Captaine <hi>Preſton,</hi> as I remember, and one more, in an indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent place betwixt the Forces on both ſides, and it was the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Gentlemen then with me, that I ſhould ſpeake to Mr. <hi>Pyne</hi> and the reſt to this purpoſe: That the Lord Marqueſſe <hi>Hert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> the Kings Lieutenant, did much wonder, that his comming into that Country ſhould be underſtood to be rather in the nature of an Enemy, then a Friend: That he was come with the Kings Commiſſion to command the Militia of that County, and to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the peace thereof: And foraſmuch as he heares, that you have put your ſelves into Armes, and are comming towards him, for which he underſtands not well the occaſion; He hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded us to let you know, that if you thinke fit to ſend ſome Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119479:4"/>unto him, and in the meane time to retreat to <hi>Somerton;</hi> and there to attend the returne of ſuch as you ſhall ſo ſend: We doe promiſe you, as we are Gentlemen, thoſe whom you ſhall thinke fit ſo to imploy, ſhall have free liberty both to come and returne at their pleaſures, and a friendly reception while they are there. And that we would joyne with them in the promoting of any thing which might ſtand with his Lordſhips honour, and truſt to grant, and might be for the peace and welfare of the Country: Mr. <hi>Pine</hi> replyed, That he would make the Gentlemen acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with what I had delivered, and that we ſhould receive an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, which accordingly was ſent unto us by Mr. <hi>Emanuell Sandys,</hi> to this effect; That they with their companies as they made their appearance, did reſolve that night to march to <hi>Glaſenbury.</hi> And accordingly they began to match up the Hill, which was an advance towards us being directly in their way, and made many ſhots firſt at us, and did wound a Gentleman, and killed his horſe under him, which we perceiving, in our owne defence, put our ſelves into ſuch a poſture as might ſecure us; and upon that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the unhappy engagement, in which there was one <hi>Osborne</hi> kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſome others were hurt, and ſome taken priſoners, amongſt which was Captaine <hi>Preſton</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sandys,</hi> to whoſe certificate hereafter mentioned, I crave leave to referre you. In this ſkirmiſh one <hi>Nicholas Ward</hi> a Drummer had many wounds by ſome of the Troopers, who made purſuance after him and ſome others who had fled into the Corne to ſave themſelves; at which time I my ſelfe, and ſome of the Kings Commanders then preſent were do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our utmoſt endeavours to ſtop our horſe from further proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Mr. <hi>Pyne</hi> and others of that party, who were fled: Yet this imployment of mine, at ſome diſtance of place from that where it ſeemes the Drummer was hurt, hath not been ſufficient enough to cleer me from the loud and falſe aſperſions of ſome, who unc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſantly made it their buſineſſe againſt me, that I with my own bloudy hands, and in cold bloud, did carbonade (as they call it) that Drummer Whereas I doe proteſt before the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, that I did not cut or draw bloud on any man that day, but made it my care to preſerve any of that party, and to reſcue as many as I ſaw any violence offered unto, and to ſuch Gentlemen as were taken priſoners, and had ſuffered by the Souldiery, I ſhewed all the civillity that poſſibly lay in my power, of which ſome of them have made very honourable teſtimonies and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgements, as by the ſaid Certificate under the ſaid Mr. <hi>Sandys</hi> his hand, to doe me Juſtice, directed to the Honourable Commiſſioners for Articles, together with the Depoſitions of the Lord <hi>Paulet</hi> and ſome others hereafter mentioned may appeare. But <hi>Ward</hi> the Drummer having once ſworne, and obtained a Judgement at Law for the dammages of a hundred pounds and upwards againſt me, findes himſelfe now bound to make good
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119479:4"/>this ſhameleſſe untruth, being obliged to ſecure one miſchiefe by acting of another. And therefore being made a Defendant to my Petition exhibited to the Honourable Court of Articles, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his Judgement ſo obtained, he did upon his appearance together with one <hi>Cady</hi> preferre a moſt ſcandalous and falſe Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition againſt me to that Court which followeth in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Right Honourable the Commiſſioners appointed by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to give reliefe to perſons upon Articles made in time of Warre.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The Humble Petition of <hi>William Cady</hi> of <hi>Taunton,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Ward</hi> of <hi>Chard</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> together with their anſwers to ſo much of the Petition of Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> exhibited to your Honours as concernes them.</head>
                  <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THat they have faithfully ſerved the Parliament from the firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the troubles againſt the publike enemy, with the expence of their bloud and eſtates, and particularly oppoſed Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>and his bloudy adherents: Wherein your Petitioners (beſides the loſſe and plunder of their eſtates by that party) have received wounds and May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemes in their bodies, whereby they are utterly diſabled to worke at their Trades; your Petitioner</hi> Cady <hi>having loſt three ſonnes in the Parliaments ſervice who were the ſtaffe of his age, and himſelfe fourteen moneths im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned in a loathſome Goale, where he was laid in Irons by the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate command of Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>for no other cauſe but his faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the Parliament. And your Petitioner</hi> Ward <hi>for the ſame cauſe had his noſe, and one of his fingers cut off, and one of his eyes was cut out, by Sir</hi> John Stawells <hi>owne cruell hand, and that in cold bloud, your ſaid Petitioner</hi> Ward <hi>being unarmed, and all without any provocation on the Petitioners part, whereby they are both of them utterly undone with their wives and children.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That they heretofore brought their ſeverall Actions againſt Sir</hi> John Stawell, <hi>wherein they have Judgements againſt him: namely your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner</hi> Cady <hi>hath a Judgement againſt Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>for</hi> 212 <hi>l. And your Petitioner</hi> Ward <hi>hath a Judgement againſt him for</hi> 107. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>s. which Judgements are ſo farre from proving a benefit to them, that they are an addition to their miſery; for they have ſpent as much money by their Judgements and attendance, and otherwiſe, as thoſe Judgements a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount unto in ſeeking after the fruits of them, and can receive none at all, and are reduced to very great want and miſery. And being now ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to appeare before your Honours in this Court, upon Sir</hi> John Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wells <hi>Petition, They are come out of their country, being ſeaven ſcore miles from</hi> London <hi>in obedience to your command, and have attended for three weeks laſt paſt, their poor wives and children being like to ſtarve at home, and themſelves no longer able to ſubſiſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They therefore humbly begge this honourable Court to take their lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119479:5"/>eſtate into your pious and tender conſideration, ſo that they may be diſmiſſed with their coſts and charges (which they have been unjuſtly put unto by the ſaid Sir</hi> John Stawell) <hi>and put to no further attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And that in regard of their extream ſufferings, even to their utter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, by the ſaid Sir</hi> John Stawells <hi>means as aforeſaid, your Honors will be pleaſed to recommend their ſad eſtate to the Parliament, to the end they may have ſome relief; For they having nothing left them where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to live, and muſt undoubtedly periſh with their diſtreſſed Families, unleſs the Lord ſhall move the heart of the Parliament and your Honors to pity their ſad eſtate, and to provide ſome preſent help for them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>William Cady.</item>
                           <item>Nicholas Ward.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Now in reſpect the truth of this Petition did never come to any proof, and reſts as a grievance upon me, I have thought it fit to remove it at this time, and upon this occaſion, by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of ſuch perſons as were there preſent, and of the other party, who as friends to Truth, do upon their Oaths and Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficates ſay as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Honorable Commiſſioners of the Court of Articles.</head>
                  <p>Emanuel Sandys <hi>of</hi> Burrough <hi>in the County of</hi> Somerſet, <hi>Gent. doth hereby declare and certifie, that he will upon his Oath ſay and depoſe, that heretofore he being with Mr.</hi> Pyne <hi>and Captain</hi> Preſton, <hi>and others, deſired, in behalf and for the good of the Country, to march to</hi> Glaſtonbury <hi>and ſo to</hi> Wells, <hi>where the Marqueſs of</hi> Hertford <hi>and others then lay, as they went from</hi> Somerton <hi>towards</hi> Glaſtonbury, <hi>going up the hill towards</hi> Marſhfills-Elm, <hi>they diſcovered a company of armed men and horſe at the top of the hill, whereupon they made a ſtand, and ſhortly after S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                     </hi> Joh. Paulet, <hi>now Lord</hi> Paulet, <hi>with S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                     </hi> Joh. Stawell <hi>Knight, and ſome others, came down the hill towards us, and ſent a meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to us, deſiring to ſpeak with ſome of us; whereupon the company deſired me</hi> Emanuel Sandys <hi>to go and ſpeak with them, with I did accordingly; when it was demanded, wherefore ſo many men came armed, and whither they meant to go; to which demand</hi> Sandys <hi>anſwered, they hearing that the Marqueſs of</hi> Hertford <hi>and others were at</hi> Wells, <hi>and intended to ſet up the Commiſſion of Aray in the County of</hi> Somerſet, <hi>they with many others had agreed that night to meet at</hi> Glaſtonbury, <hi>and the next day to go to</hi> Wells <hi>to ſpeak with the ſaid Marqueſs</hi> Hertford: <hi>When the ſaid Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>and others deſired that the company ſhould go back to</hi> Somerton, <hi>and appoint ſome men to go and ſpeak with the Marqueſs, and they would promiſe that whoſoever would come to them, and go with them to the Marqueſs, they ſhould come, go, and return freely and quietly, and in the mean time they at</hi> Somerton <hi>ſhould reſt there in ſafety; wherewith</hi> Sandys <hi>acquainted Mr.</hi> Pyne, <hi>Captain</hi> Preſton,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119479:5"/>
                     <hi>and others then there, who then ſent again</hi> Sandys <hi>with Mr.</hi> Sanders, <hi>to tell Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>and their company, that they intended not to return, but to go on to</hi> Glaſtonbury <hi>that night; when they replyed, we ſhould do what we pleaſed; and thereupon Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>and the reſt of that company rode up the hill to their company, and</hi> Sandys <hi>and</hi> Sanders <hi>returned to their company, and afterwards Captain</hi> Preſton <hi>and the company offering to march up the hill in two bodies, the company on the hill ſhot at us ſeveral times, and we at them; and thereupon ſome of the company and Mr.</hi> Pyne <hi>flod, and a Troop of Souldiers coming down the hill, took Captain</hi> Preſton <hi>and</hi> Sandys, <hi>and hurt</hi> Sandys; <hi>and took from them their moneys, horſes and weapons, and preſently after came the now Lord</hi> Paulet <hi>and Sir</hi> John Stawell, <hi>and took from the Souldiers</hi> Preſton <hi>and</hi> Sandys, <hi>who elſe had been killed, and the ſame night carried them to</hi> Wells, <hi>where they had fair quarter, and for that the Souldiers had taken their mony from them, Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>Gentleman-like delivered to</hi> Sandys <hi>forty ſhillings, which</hi> Sandys <hi>took for a civil reſpect, and ſhortly after his enlargement payd him again, and thanked him for his favor and kinde uſage, and doth verily believe that many lives and much blood was that time ſaved, by the onely means of the ſaid Sir</hi> John Stawell, <hi>who then and at other times ever behaved himſelf as a lover of his Country.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Lordſhips, &amp;c. moſt humble Servant, <hi>Emmanuel Sandys.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="interrogation">
               <body>
                  <head>The Examination of <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Paulet</hi> of <hi>Hinton St. George</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> of the age of ſeven and thirty years or thereabouts, produced on the behalf of Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> this twentieth day of <hi>June, 1653.</hi> by vertue of the Order of the Commiſſioners for Articles, and upon his Oath taken the fifteenth of the ſaid Month.</head>
                  <p>TO the 21. Interrogatory he ſaith and depoſeth,
<note place="margin">L. <hi>Paulet.</hi>
                     </note> that he was at <hi>Marſhals-Elm,</hi> in the Interrogatory mentioned in the year 1642. which, as neer as he can remember, was on the fourth day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> in that year, where the late Kings forces, under the command of the Marqueſs of <hi>Hertford,</hi> and the Forces of the Parliament, under the conduct of <hi>John Pyne,</hi> Eſq; and Captain <hi>Preſton,</hi> did engage: And ſaith, that Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatory mentioned, was in the ſaid engagement on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the King, and did continue very neer this Deponent du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all the time of that Action and Engagement, and for a great part of that day; And that he doth remember that the ſaid Sir <hi>John</hi> did not in all that ſervice and fight, either diſcharge his piſtol, or hurt or ſtrike at any man, but doth very well remember, that after the firſt charge made, and the flight of the Forces for the Parliament down the hill there into a lane at the foot thereof,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119479:6"/>he the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> together with this Deponent, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other Gentlemen, did make a ſtand at the entering into the the ſaid lane, and did there ſtop the further purſuit of the Horſe then charging on the behalf of the King, &amp; ſtayd there for almoſt half an hour before he and they retreated to the top of the hill: And ſaith, that he did not ſee the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> at any time of the day leave the way, or go out of the ſame, to ſearch the Corn on either hand for ſuch who were hid there after the charge of the Horſe, as aforeſaid: And ſaith, that the aforeſaid Captain <hi>Preſton,</hi> and one Mr. <hi>Sandys,</hi> was that day and upon that charge taken priſoners, and as this Deponent conceiveth, and to the beſt of his remembrance, the ſaid priſoners were by the advice, and at the deſire of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> and other the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen in that Action, releaſed and ſet at liberty by the ſaid Marqueſs of <hi>Hertford,</hi> in a ſhort time after their being taken priſoners as aforeſaid, and had their Horſes and Arms, and what ever they could claim as belonging unto them, and could be found, delivered unto them; and further ſaith, that during their reſtraint they were uſed with very fair reſpect and civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
                  <p>To the 22. Interrogatory this Deponent ſaith and depoſeth, that he doth not know the Drummer in the Interrogatory men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, neither did he ſee him during the fight in the precedent Interrogatory mentioned; but ſaith, that he hath ſince heard, that the ſaid Drummer was hurt and wounded by one <hi>Crocker,</hi> a Trooper in the ſervice of the King in that fight: And ſaith, that he doth believe in his conſcience that the ſaid Drummer was not hurt by the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> which he doth with the more confidence depoſe, for that the ſaid Sir <hi>John</hi> and this Deponent kept together all the time of that Action, and did never ſtir out of the high-way, there being a Ditch or a ſmall fence on each ſide thereof, and Corn-fields, into which many did fly for ſhelter; and further to this Interrogatory cannot depoſe.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="interrogation">
               <body>
                  <head>The Examination of <hi>Robert Knight</hi> of <hi>Hill-Biſhop</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> Gent. of the age of thirty years, or thereabouts, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced on the behalf of Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> according to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Commiſſioners for Relief upon Articles of War, upon his Oath before the ſaid Commiſſioners the <hi>21</hi> of this inſtant <hi>June,</hi> took the <hi>27</hi> of the ſaid Month.</head>
                  <p>TO the 21 Interrogatory he ſaith and depoſeth,
<note place="margin">Robert Knight.</note> that he was at <hi>Marſhals-Elm</hi> in the Interrogatory mentioned, and as neer as he can remember about the time therein ſet forth; And ſaith, that he was there in the Troop of Sir <hi>Francis Hawley,</hi> who was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ere in command, together with Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> and the now Lord <hi>Paulet;</hi> and upon his Oath ſaith, that he doth very well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119479:6"/>when the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> with the reſt, firſt came to the top of the Hill neer <hi>Marſhals-Elm,</hi> they diſcovered ſome For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at the bottom of the Hill, and that after ſome meſſage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, there was a direction given to fall on, which being done, the Parliaments party immediately fled, and ſome of them were taken priſoners; but by whom any were killed or taken priſoners, he cannot expreſly ſet forth; but ſaith, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth in his conſcience that the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> did not that day hurt or wound any man, for that he this Deponent doth very well remember, that the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> with the now Lord <hi>Paulet,</hi> then Sir <hi>John Paulet,</hi> did ſtop the Souldiers in the entrance of the lane, into which the ſaid Forces fled, from pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing of them; And is very confident, that the ſaid Sir <hi>John</hi> did not ſtir out of the high-way into the Corn on either ſide of the way all that day; which he knoweth the better to depoſe, for that he kept ſtill very neer him: And ſaith, that ſuch who did not retreat into the ſaid lane, did hide themſelves in the Corn in the ſide of the way: And further to this Interrogatory he cannot depoſe.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="interrogation">
               <body>
                  <head>The Examination of <hi>William Stucky</hi> of <hi>Chillington</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> yeoman, of the age of three and thirty years, or thereabouts, produced on the behalf of Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> and taken the <hi>27</hi> of <hi>June, 1653.</hi> by vertue of the Order of the Commiſſioners for Relief upon Articles of War, of the <hi>16</hi> of <hi>February</hi> laſt paſt, and upon his Oath taken the <hi>24</hi> of <hi>June</hi> laſt paſt.</head>
                  <p>TO the 21 and 22 Interrogatories this Deponent ſaith and depoſeth, that he, in the beginning of the late Wars,
<note place="margin">William Stucky.</note> was a Trooper under the command of Sir <hi>Francis Hawley,</hi> and marched with him in his Troop from <hi>Wells</hi> to <hi>Marſhals-Elm</hi> in the Interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatories mentioned; And ſaith, that being come thither, they were ordered to charge ſome forces of the Country, which were there under the command of Captain <hi>Preſton;</hi> and that the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> was in the firſt Rank of the ſaid Troop: And he this Examinant upon his Oath ſaith, that upon the firſt charge the ſaid Forces fled, being routed, and ſome fled into the Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fields in the ſide of the high-way; And that ſo ſoon as the ſaid Forces were ſo routed, and fled, the Troop was commanded by the ſaid Sir <hi>Francis Hawley</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to ſtop in their purſuit, and rally again, and march back up the Hill, which was accordingly done, Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> being then in the head of the Troop, having with him Captain <hi>Preſton</hi> and one Mr <hi>Sandys,</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners that day taken; And ſaith, that as the ſaid Troop march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed back, as aforeſaid, he this Examinate, with ſome of the Troop then in the Reer, rode into the Corn-fields by the way ſide, to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119479:7"/>ſearch after ſuch as were thought might be hid in the Corn; And that there was one <hi>Thomas Crocker</hi> of the ſame Troop amongſt us, who found in the corn one <hi>Nicholas Ward</hi> a Drummer of <hi>Chard,</hi> and with his ſword gave him divers wounds and cuts, and as this Deponent believeth would have killed him, if he had not begged for his life: And this Examinate faith, that he ſaw the ſaid <hi>Crocker</hi> ſo wound the ſaid <hi>Ward;</hi> and that before the ſaid wounds ſo given, as aforeſaid, this Deponent did not perceive any hurt or wounds the ſaid Drummer had, he having left his Drum in the high-way, and was hid in the corn as aforeſaid: And he this Deponent laſtly ſaith, that he did not at all that day ſee the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> either diſcharge his Piſtol, or hurt any man with his ſword, or go out of the road-way upon the charge or Retreat; but when he returned out of the corn-fields as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, he found the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> with the ſaid Troop on the top of the Hill, ready to march back to <hi>Wells;</hi> and further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth not.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="deposition">
               <body>
                  <head>Robert Vax <hi>of</hi> Weſtham <hi>in the County of</hi> Eſſex <hi>being depoſed, maketh Oath, and ſaith.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THat this Deponent, being formerly a ſervant unto Mr. <hi>Emanuel Sandys</hi> of <hi>Petherton</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> was with his ſaid Maſter in the party commanded by Captain <hi>Preſton</hi> of the ſaid County, and marching, as this Deponent verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth, towards <hi>Glaſtonbury,</hi> they deſcryed a party of Horſe on the top of an Hill called <hi>Marſhals-Elm,</hi> the which party was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the command (as this Deponent hath been ſince informed) of the Marqueſs of <hi>Hertford,</hi> in which party was Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> and divers other Gentlemen, which this Deponent did then ſee. And further this Deponent maketh Oath, and ſaith, that before the Engagement he both ſaw Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> come down the Hill, and alſo heard him call unto &amp; demand of Capt. <hi>Preſton,</hi> with the Officers of our party, whither they were marching; unto whom Captain <hi>Preſton</hi> replyed, that he intended to march to <hi>Glaſtonbury</hi> that night: whereupon the ſaid <hi>Stawell</hi> deſired him to march back with his company to <hi>Somerton,</hi> promiſing him that if he would ſend any perſon or perſons of his company to <hi>Glaſtonbury, Wells,</hi> or to the Marqueſs of <hi>Hertford,</hi> that they ſhould be permitted to paſs without any moleſtation: to which the ſaid Captain <hi>Preſton</hi> replyed, that he reſolved to march that night to <hi>Glaſtonbury</hi> aforeſaid; and as he was marching up the Hill, called <hi>Marſhals-Elm,</hi> heard one of the party under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Marqueſs to ſay, that if they advanced any further they would fire on them: And further this Deponent faith, that at the time of the Engagement he was then preſent when the ſaid <hi>Sandys</hi> was taken priſoner, and that he heard the ſaid Sir
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119479:7"/>
                     <hi>John Stawell</hi> to call and ſay unto ſome of that party then about the ſaid priſoner, deſiring them to hold their hands, in that he knew him to be an honeſt Gentleman; further ſaying, that it was Mr <hi>Sandys</hi> of <hi>Petherton:</hi> And this Deponent further ſaith, that immediately after the taking of the ſaid <hi>Sandys</hi> Priſoner, he this Deponent did ſee Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> ride down to the foot of the Hill, and did then and there, in the view of this Deponent, fall about and endevor to prevent the purſuit, cauſing many of that party to return back from purſuing the ſaid party then with Captain <hi>Preſton:</hi> And this Deponent maketh Oath and ſaith, that being encompaſſed and amongſt the Enemy, and endeavor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make his eſcape as he thought towards <hi>Somerton,</hi> and riding through a corn-field, he ſaw <hi>Nicholas Ward,</hi> then Drummer to Captain <hi>Preſton,</hi> encompaſſed by two Souldiers on horſeback, and that this Deponent did ſee one of the ſaid Souldiers to give him the ſaid <hi>Ward</hi> ſeveral blows with his ſword: And further this Deponent ſaith, that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> was not the party, nor then preſent when the ſaid <hi>Ward</hi> was wounded, for as much as the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> was at that inſtant time ſtanding at the foot of the Hill: And this Deponent ſaith, that one of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, then preſent at the wounding of <hi>Ward,</hi> was named <hi>Crocker,</hi> which formerly was a Retainer to the Lord <hi>Paulet:</hi> And further this Deponent maketh Oath and ſaith, that as he was making his eſcape, was overtaken by three Horſemen within half a mile of <hi>Somerton,</hi> who gave him ſeveral wounds, leaving him in the high-way; but that any or either of the aforeſaid wounds were given him by the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> this Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſaith not: And further this Deponent ſaith, that being wounded, he was brought to <hi>Somerton;</hi> and not being able, by reaſon of his wounds, to march with his company, was with divers others maimed and wounded men left behinde in the ſaid Town: And this Deponent ſaith, that within three days after this Deponent's being there, the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> with ſeveral others of that party, came into the ſaid Town to quarter; and that the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> with divers others of that party, did give ſeveral ſums of Mony unto many of the wounded and maimed Souldiers ſo left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, whereof this Deponent received a part (to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, as neer as he this Deponent can remember, of about four pounds:) And further this Deponent ſaith not.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Septemb.</hi> 28. 1653.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Sworn <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>ROBERT VAY.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>THO. BENET.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119479:8"/>
            <p>And as concerning the charge of <hi>Cady</hi> that he was kept a priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for the ſpace of fourteen moneths, and laid in Irons by my immediate command, the truth is, I found him a priſoner in the Caſtle of <hi>Taunton</hi> when I firſt took that command upon me, and did by my <hi>Mitimus</hi> to the Keeper of <hi>Ivelcheſter</hi> onely remove him from <hi>Taunton</hi> thither as I did one <hi>England,</hi> who was likewiſe ſent by the ſame <hi>Mitimus,</hi> and after that ſome others for the eaſe of the Caſtle of <hi>Taunton,</hi> where they were improperly kept, <hi>England</hi> a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle after upon his requeſt unto me was diſcharged, but <hi>Cady</hi> could not have the like favour, for that he was a priſoner at Law upon an Action of Debt laid upon him at his firſt comming thither. And this will be teſtified by Mr. <hi>Browne</hi> the Keeper of the Goale, who did then receive him. As alſo that I never gave him (who hath been the Keeper of that priſon many yeares) either as touching <hi>Cady</hi> or any priſoner elſe, ſent unto him directions for the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him or any other in Irons, neither doth the <hi>Mitimus</hi> by which he was ſo ſent give any ſuch directions, onely I required the ſafe keeping of them till their Deliverance according to Law. All which I humbly ſubmit to your judgements and theſe proofes conſidered, whether it is poſſible for me to be guilty of ſo much bloud and cruelty as is mentioned in the Petition.</p>
            <p>After which about the beginning of <hi>June,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord 1643. waiting upon the Marqueſſe of <hi>Hertford</hi> by the late Kings command from <hi>Oxford</hi> into the Weſt, with ſuch Forces as then were under his Lordſhips command, we marched towards the Towne of <hi>Taunton,</hi> and comming with conſiderable For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces neer the Towne, whereby they in the Towne and Caſtle deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berating their own ſafety and welfare, and finding by the reſult of their conſultation (as it ſeemes that they were not of any equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſtrength to ſtand out, they ſent two of the Townſmen, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Chapline</hi> (as I remember their then Major) and one Mr. <hi>Powell</hi> an Apothecary, to my Lord Marqueſſe to make their conditions, but as the truth did after appeare, it was for no other end but that in that ſpace of time the Souldiers and Forces might quit the Towne, and ſave themſelves and what they had there by flight, which the Lord Marqueſſe and his party perceiving, did preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enter the Towne without any conceſſion at all. Whereupon it was my humble requeſt to the Marqueſſe and Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> then his Lieutenant Generall, that in regard there had been an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by the Towneſmen of a Fine to be paid to preſerve their Towne from plunder, and their perſons from violence, that they would be pleaſed that a reaſonable Fine might be impoſed, and the Towne kept free from any ſuch violence or hoſtile mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation (as they had juſt reaſon to feare, as the caſe then ſtood with them) at which requeſt of mine my Lord Marqueſſe was pleaſed to make a publike Proclamation throughout his Army to prohibite all the Souldiery of what degree ſoever, that they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119479:8"/>ſhould not offer any violence to their perſons or take their goods or in any manner doe them dammage upon paine of death. The Fine which was afterwards agreed upon betwixt my Lord Marqueſſe, his Councell of Warre, and the Towne, was 8000. <hi>l.</hi> as I have heard, which they promiſed ſhould faithfully be ſatisfied without delay, upon which the buſineſſe being thus ſetled, the Marqueſſe and the Prince his Lieutenant Generall, and the reſt of his Councell conſulted about the deputing a Governour, ſuch a one as ſhould anſwer the expectation of the Marqueſſe, and with all ſhould be well pleaſing to the Towne and Country adjacent; during which deliberation the Townſmen of <hi>Taunton</hi> conceiving themſelves concerned, in the concluſion thought fit to preferre their Petition to have ſuch a Governour as was of birth and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, of their own Countrey, from whom as it ſeemes they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed they might have eaſe and favour; which Petition as it was exhibited by the then chiefeſt Inhabitants, is in very words thus:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>To his Highneſſe <hi>Prince Maurice,</hi> and to his Excellency the Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe and Earle of <hi>Hertford,</hi> Generall of his Majeſties Forces in the Weſt.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The humble Petition of the Inhabitants of the Town of <hi>Taunton.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEing very ſenſible of the great oppreſſions we have ſuffered, and the miſeries to which we are reduced under that government, and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thoſe Governours, to whom neceſſity hath of late times enforced our ſubjection, and yet with ſome comfort reſenting thoſe happy times wherein the Lawes and Juſtice of this Kingdome were by the hands of the noble Gentry of theſe parts ſo diſpenſed amongſt us that every man enjoyed his owne, his liberty, his property, and lived a moſt happy people under a moſt gratious Soveraigne, and being deſirous to be againe brought as neere as may be to the ſame happy condition, doe in all humillity beſeech your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Excellency will vouchſafe to aſſigne ſome Gentleman of birth and honour neere adjoyning to us, to be our Governour, (who to your Highneſſe and your Excellency ſhall ſeeme fit, and under whoſe protection we may enjoy the almoſt forgot felioities of former times, our liberties and ſafeties. And we ſhall account our ſelves moſt happy, and will ever thankefully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge your graces and favours to us, and pray for your Highneſſe and Excellencies proſperities with increaſe of happineſſe and honour.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>After which Petition preferred, the Townſmen did become earneſt ſuiters to the Marqueſſe, that he would be pleaſed to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne me in particular and by name their Governour, (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they had left it indefinitely to the Marqueſſe his diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to appoint any of the Gentlemen of that Country ſo quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied as they expreſſed in their Petition, whereupon the Marqueſſe willing to give them ſuch ſatisfaction as might oblige them, did
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119479:9"/>deſire me to take the government up on me. But I very well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the nature of the people, and how that Towne had dealt with me for my good will towards them (who had never in all my life been wanting in any thing wherein I might in all neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourly manner befriend them.) In the third yeare of the late King, at which time they preferred Articles grounded upon ſcandalous and falſe ſuggeſtions againſt me unto the Parliament. The dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of any one of which in caſe they could have made them good againſt me might have coſt me my life.</p>
            <p>Nor was their violent proſecution of the ſaid Articles (by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for a Serjeant at Armes by whom I was commanded to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Houſe at that time) to be forgotten, although they were not able in the leaſt manner to faſten any thing upon me that might juſtly demerit ſo much as the rebuke of the houſe or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee to whom it was referred.</p>
            <p>All which or to the like effect, I urged unto the Marqueſſe, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and heartily deſiring his Lordſhip that he would be pleaſed to excuſe me, their former practices adminiſtring good reaſon for my refuſall; Inſomuch as the Marqueſſe holding himſelfe ſatisfied did place the government upon a perſon of honour and quality of the county, who had the deputation for ſome time, during which the Towne continued very Inceſſantly to importune his Lordſhip that I might be the man who ſhould have the command over them, and thinking it then a conſiderable part of their inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, did make uſe of very many Gentlemen and perſons of quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to mediate for them, and to perſwade me to entertaine it, and in their own perſons did often ſollicite me to accept of a commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to that purpoſe: Yet theſe their endeavours notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I did refuſe.</p>
            <p>But his Lordſhips importunity growing to that height that I could not with good manners withſtand him, I did humbly pray his Lordſhip, that he would lay aſide his requeſt unto me, as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting a latitude or ſcope to my denyall, and to command me to it, and I ſhould obey him as my Generall, upon which my Lord replyed, if you will excuſe the terme, I doe command you: And thus I accepted my commiſſion, the chiefeſt of the Towne being then preſent and importuning the ſame, the commiſſion follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in theſe words:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="commission">
               <body>
                  <p>WIlliam, <hi>Marqueſſe and Earle of</hi> Hertford, <hi>Viſcount Beauchampt Lord</hi> Seymor, <hi>one of his Majeſties most honourable Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and Lieutenant Generall of his Majeſties Forces in the Weſt: To Sir</hi> John Stawell, <hi>Knight of the honourable order of the</hi> Bath <hi>greeting. By vertue of the authority and power given from our Soveraigne Lord King</hi> Charles, <hi>under the great Seal of</hi> England, <hi>as Lieutenant Generall as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, I doe hereby conſtitute and appoint you the ſaid Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>to be Governour of the Towne and Caſtle of</hi> Taunton, <hi>and the Pariſh of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119479:9"/>St.</hi> James <hi>thereunto adjoyning, ſcituate in the County of</hi> Somerſet, <hi>and the Garriſon therein, and Forces thereof, and doe give unto you full power and authority in his Majeſties name and for his ſervice, the ſaid ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>riſon and Forces as Governour to command, arm, diſcipline, traine, and order in warlike manner, and with them to fortifie the ſaid Towne, Caſtle, and Pariſh, and defend and preſerve the ſame againſt all his Majeſties enemies whatſoever to the utmoſt of your abilities, and further exerciſe Marſhall Law within the ſaid Towne, caſtle, and pariſh upon all offenders deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſame, and to doe, performe, and execute all ſuch act and acts, thing and things, as to the Office of a Governour of a Towne, caſtle, and Pariſh doth of right appeartaine and belong, willing and commanding all Officers and Souldiers of the ſaid Garriſen, together with the Inhabitants of the ſaid Towne, caſtle, and Pariſh to obey you as their ſaid Governour according to this your commiſſion, as alſo all ſuch Officers as you ſhall appoint under your hand and ſeal for the furtherance and advancement of his Majeſties ſervice: And you your ſelfe to obſerve and follow all ſuch orders and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections as you ſhall from time to time receive from his Majeſty, my ſelfe, or my Lieutenant Generall according to the occaſion and diſcipline of Warre.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given under my hand and ſeal at <hi>Taunton</hi>
                        <date> this eighth day of <hi>June</hi> in the <hi>19.</hi> yeare of his Majeſties Raigne.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>HERTFORD.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Together with this Commiſſion I had two other Commiſſions, the one for the raiſing of a Regiment of Horſe and Dragoones, the other for the raiſing of a Regiment of 1500. Foot, which I forbeare to inſert for brevities ſake.</p>
            <p>That very morning I received my Commiſſion my Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe marched out of the Towne, leaving me to the ordering of my Garriſon, upon which I thought fit to take a view of the Caſtle, to the end I might diſpoſe and regulate matters as might anſwer my charge and truſt, where when I came, I found to the number of 60. priſoners or thereabout, whoſe impriſonment in that place I did not thinke convenient: And therefore did pray the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Sir <hi>William Portman</hi> and Mr. <hi>John Symes,</hi> two of the Deputy Lieutenants of the County and Juſtices of the peace, and were neighbours, to adviſe about the diſpoſing of them, who did at my requeſt come unto me to the Caſtle, where we called all the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners before us, and examined the reaſons of their ſeverall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitments, and for ſo many as we found committed by <hi>Mittimus,</hi> &amp; their offence of ſuch a nature as that they could not be delivered without a due courſe of Law, thoſe were detained, amongſt which was Mr. <hi>Chaplaine,</hi> Mr. <hi>Powell</hi> the Apothecary, and the aforenamed <hi>Cady,</hi> for which they and ſome others have brought their ſeverall Actions againſt me, and recovered great ſums of money; And for ſo many as we found, who were not committed by <hi>Mittimus,</hi> or for ſlight offences, or by perſons of no ſufficient authority for that purpoſe (who were as I remember the greater part) we diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119479:10"/>and the reſt were ſent to <hi>Ivelcheſter</hi> and other places.</p>
            <p>The priſoners being thus diſpoſed of, I began to conſider of ſuch things as might beſt conduce to the maintenance of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, for the payment of thoſe Souldiers which the Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe left me for making good the Garriſon untill I had levyed Souldiers of my own: And having no contribution at that time aſſigned me, I was enforced to call upon the Town to proportion a rate for the collecting of the Fine afore-mentioned and agreed upon for a compoſition with the Marqueſſe upon his entry, and for the receipt of which he gave me order upon his departure, which is as followeth:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="order">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Ordered at</hi> Taunton <hi>the ninth day of</hi> June, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1643.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IT is ordered that Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>ſhall receive of the Inhabitants of this Towne of</hi> Taunton <hi>and the Pariſh of</hi> St.
<note place="margin">Somerſet.</note> James, <hi>the ſum of eight thouſand pounds, being the ſum ſet downe and impoſed upon them by his Highneſſe, his Excellency, and the councell of Warre: And if it ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare unto him that any perſon or perſons ſhall be overcharged with the ſaid Taxe or payment in reſpect of their eſtates or quality, the ſaid Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>hath power by this to Aſſeſſe any other man who is omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and not already rated, for the eaſe of ſuch parties as ſhall have juſt cauſe to have reliefe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>HERTFORD.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Upon which I called upon the Towne for no make payment of the ſame, in regard the neceſſity of my occaſions did ſo require. But they having, as I found by their notes and Acquittances which they produced, paid my Lord Marqueſſe the ſum of 500 <hi>l.</hi> or neer thereabouts, did excuſe themſelves as not able to raiſe any more at preſent, ſo that I was conſtrained to take ſuch payment as they would make, and I did receive of them in all at ſeverall times the ſum of 500. <hi>l.</hi> more or thereabout as I remember, which was to reſt upon account; yet before I could receive any I was conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to commit ſome of them, for which they likewiſe have brought their Actions.</p>
            <p>Yet it is true, that when the late King was come to the City of <hi>Briſtoll</hi> ſhortly after his Forces had taken it, he being acquainted with the ſum of 8000. <hi>l.</hi> impoſed upon <hi>Taunton,</hi> did ſend unto me for to require 2000. <hi>l.</hi> of it, and ſend it, unto him with all ſpeed, whereupon I acquainted the Towne with it, and they excuſing themſelves with the loſſe of Trade which was that they lived by, did ſeeme very unwilling to raiſe any more above the 1000. <hi>l.</hi> already paid, Inſomuch that I according to my then duty to the late Kings commands, did acquaint them, that if they did not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the money he ſent for, I muſt take ſome courſe with them of compulſion, upon which they departed, and did by the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119479:10"/>collect the ſum of 850. <hi>l.</hi> which was all that I could get or receive from them, and this being ſhort of what the late King was pleaſed to command, I did borrow of one Mr. <hi>Porter</hi> a Scrivener, upon my own account, the ſum of 100. <hi>l.</hi> for which I gave Bond, and of Doctor <hi>Byham</hi> I had 50. <hi>l.</hi> more to make up the ſum col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected 1000. but in reſpect it did not anſwer the late Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, I did my ſelfe in perſon carry that ſum unto Briſtoll, and did acquaint the late King with the difficulty that I had in raiſing of that ſum, and with the preſent condition of the Towne, and made that an excuſe for the reſt, inſomuch as when the late King was ſatisfied from me of their inability, he was pleaſed to leave the remainder of the 8000. <hi>l.</hi> to my diſcretion, ſo as to give ſuch an abatement as I ſhould think fit.</p>
            <p>After which I continued in my command, as I remember, by the ſpace of ſix moneths; and although I had power and authority ſufficient to have required the reſt, yet I was ſo friendly unto them, that they paying their contribution in proportion with the reſt of the Country, I never pretended any occaſion for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement of the reſt; ſo that of the whole ſum of 8000. <hi>l.</hi> impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, by my mediation to the King for his favor, and my Kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and good will to that Towne, I ſaved unto them the ſum of 6000. <hi>l.</hi> or thereabouts, beſides the 150. <hi>l.</hi> lent them of my own, which is to this day unpaid, for which they have made me ſince a very ill requitall: for after that I had raiſed part of my Regiment, which I was to raiſe by my Lord Marqueſſe his commiſſion, and had ſent to the Army the 500. Foot which my Lord Marqueſſe had left me at my firſt taking the command of the Towne upon me, and had ſupplyed that want with part of my own Regiment raiſed, I received orders from the late King to ſend unto the Lord <hi>Paulet,</hi> who then lay before <hi>Lime,</hi> 100. of my Garriſon Souldiers for his aſſiſtance, and hereupon I gave order to Captaine <hi>Robert Clarke</hi> with his Officers and company to march accordingly: but the Captaine not liking his march, took occaſion to goe to his own houſe not farre from the Towne, ſo that by reaſon of his abſence ſome of his Officers grew likewiſe out of temper, which dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous infection did at length ſpread through the whole company, ſo that there was not a man but was tainted, unleſſe it was the Captaines brother, who was his Lieutenant and a ſtout Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, who in his Captaines abſence willingly took the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand upon him, and received orders accordingly; but (as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) the morning that they were to begin their march the whole company did mutiny for want of a fortnights pay that was then behinde; And in regard that ſuch demands were unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly made at ſuch a time as they were to performe their duty, I did commit ſome of the Officers and Souldiers who were moſt faulty, amongſt whom was one <hi>Chriſtopher <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iccary,</hi> and had an intent to have proceeded againſt him as the principall mutineer at a Court of War.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:119479:11"/>
            <p>The firſt day being ſpent in this diſorder, many of them who were committed did that night make ſuit to me for their releaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, promiſing that they would readily march with the reſt of their company the next morning, and be thenceforth obedient to command: thereupon for their better encouragement, I gave their Lieutenant then Captaine 50 <hi>l.</hi> in the head of his company, and did remit both impriſonment and the offence committed the day before: But as they marched through the Towne they tooke occaſion to complaine that their Armes were not fixt, and in the middle of the Street, I following them in the Reare to ſee them out of Towne, before my face they threw downe all their Armes and would not march unleſſe they might have ſuch Armes as might ſecure their lives by doing ſervice, and <hi>Viccary</hi> who was pardoned as I have ſaid before, and releaſed of his impriſonment, when I told him I would ſee him hanged for this mutiny, he cryed out one and all, and after him the whole company did the like.</p>
            <p>Hereupon I commanded <hi>Viccary</hi> the ſecond time to priſon, and had a full purpoſe (as by Lawes military I might well juſtifie) to have made him an example. But that night alſo the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany did ſue to me for his releaſe and pardon, promiſing that the next morning they would all march moſt willingly, upon which I was contented once more to enlarge him and remit his offence. And to take away all cauſes which might countenance ſuch diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I did on the next morning before their march deliver ten or twelve muſkets, out of the Magazine for ſo many as I found in any kinde defective, and being thus ſatisfied (as I ſuppoſed) I marched with them againe to the utmoſt Gate of the Towne, but after I had left them, and before I was returned to my Quarters, I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the Lieutenant that they had throwne downe their Armes within halfe a mile of the Towne in the Highway, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to march no further; and ſtealing back into the Town that night few of them could be found, but on the next morning perceiving the mutiney to be growne to a very great height, I commanded ſtrict guardes to be kept upon the gates and out-lets of the Towne, and Enſigne <hi>Atherton</hi> having command of one of the Gates, and ſeeing <hi>Viccary,</hi> and knowing him to be the ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leader in the ſeverall mutinies, did as he offered to go through the Gate with twenty more of the Souldiers or thereabout, whom he had ſeduced accuſe him for the mutiny in refuſing to march being thereunto commanded, to whom the ſaid <hi>Viccary</hi> made anſwer in theſe words (by god I will not go) ſtirring up divers of his fellow Souldiers to the like mutiny; whereupon the Enſigne going about to lay hands on him, he preſented his Muſket at him, but being prevented by the Souldiers upon the Guard, he was brought to the Caſtle and there ſecured.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the proceedings againſt him might be with the better advice, I prayed Captaine <hi>Dyer</hi> to requeſt Sir. <hi>William Port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119479:11"/>and Mr. <hi>Syms,</hi> two of the Deputy Lieutenants of the County to be preſent and aſſiſtant, who came accordingly, and did ſir in the Court of warre, which I called for that purpoſe, conſiſting of fifteen or ſixteen Officers, at which time the Articles for mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y and refuſing to goe upon command according to the late Kings military orders were read againſt the ſaid <hi>Viccary,</hi> and was upon the oath of the Enſigne and others made good againſt him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he had ſentence of death paſſed upon him by a generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and was ſhortly after executed accordingly.</p>
            <p>For this long relation I muſt humbly crave your pardon for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming upon your patience, which I have done the rather for that I may remonſtrate my proceedings concerning the ſaid <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iccary,</hi> which the Towne of <hi>Taunton</hi> hath ſo much preſſed againſt me to the hazzard of my life, notwithſtanding my kindeneſſe ſundry wayes ſhewed towards them: and that during all the time that I was their Governour, which was fully a yeare, I never received for my own uſe any one farthing of them, either in money or in any other acknowledgements, but did make it my whole endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to protect them and all that was theirs from any violence. And it is alſo true, that I had as friendly a reſpect unto the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and having the ſequeſtration of Mr. <hi>Alexander Pophams</hi> Eſtate at <hi>Wellington,</hi> Colonell <hi>Ceelyes</hi> Eſtate neer <hi>Taunton,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Wens</hi> Eſtate in the Pariſh of <hi>Laurence Liddiard,</hi> aſſigned me by way of Sequeſtration towards the maintenance of my Garriſon, and before any contribution of the Country were allotted unto me, I doe averre, that for the ſpace of a whole yeare that theſe ſeverall Eſtates were in my poſſeſſion, there was not taken by my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand (more then ſeaven or eight Loades of Hay in a time of great neceſſity (which was on Colonell <hi>Ceelyes</hi> Eſtate) and the rateable contributions with the reſt of the County) the value of ſix pence but did protect their Tenants and ſervants by them appointed for the management thereof for their uſe and beſt advantage.</p>
            <p>Yet this faire uſage notwithſtanding Mr. <hi>Ceely</hi> hath commenced and proſecuted an Action againſt me, and obtained a Judgement for 157. <hi>l.</hi> dammages, whereas intruth I did upon his wives re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt in his abſence ſuffer her to enjoy the whole benefit, except the Hay above mentioned without any ſubſtraction ſave the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table contribution.</p>
            <p>Two other particulars I ſhall preſume to relate to wipe off the calumny that is thrown upon me, and to leave it to your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the firſt was this, Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> ſucceeding my Lord the Marqueſſe of <hi>Hertford</hi> in the command of the Weſterne Forces, there came unto his hands (by what meanes I know not) a Bond for the payment of 200. <hi>l.</hi> which of right did belong unto one who he was pleaſed to call a Delinquent, and was due from Mr. <hi>Chaplaine</hi> of <hi>Taunton,</hi> which Bond he ſent in a Letter incloſed unto me, and gave me order either to receive the mony for the late
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119479:12"/>Kings ſervice, or to commit him to priſon untill he ſhould ſatisfie the ſame: I made Mr. <hi>Chaplaine</hi> herewith acquainted, and ſhewed him the Princes Letter, together with the Bond, he acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Debt, but made many proteſtations to me touching the weakeneſſe of his eſtate at that time, inſomuch that he could not poſſibly pay the money, and did leave it unto me as touching his Impriſonment. I did very much pity the old man, and did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke my ſelfe how I might in the beſt manner befriend him. I told him the Prince would expect to have his orders obeyed, and if I could not give him ſatisfaction as to the mony or to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, happily he might be ſent for and put into the cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Marſhall of the Army, and ſo his dayes by hard uſage might be ſhortned; wherefore I wiſhed him that he would give me leave to impriſon him (for without his conſent I would not doe it) which the old man thought well of as his caſe ſtood, and gave me his thanks, and I forthwith wrote my Letter unto the Prince, that Mr. <hi>Chaplaine</hi> having no mony, had ſubmitted himſelf unto his Impriſonment. That he was a very aged man, and could not brook his impriſonment long, and that as I was the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the place, it was my duty to protect every man in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty as farre as I could, and ſince it was contrary to right to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force that from him (who was admitted to his compoſition with the reſt of that Towne upon the Marqueſſe his entry) which he was lyable to repay unto his Creditors, I beſought him to be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable unto him; whereupon the Prince did returne me this anſwer (as I doe remember) That he was a ſtranger here, and did not know the Lawes of the Country, and therefore did wholly referre the matter to my diſcretion; which expreſſe I did no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner receive but I went immediately in perſon to him, and ſet him at liberty. And for this impriſonment, which was but during the ſpace of a night or two at the moſt, untill my meſſenger returned, and was ſo ſucceſſefull unto him as to ſave his 200. <hi>l.</hi> he hath brought hsi Action and recovered 313. <hi>l.</hi> in dammages againſt me.</p>
            <p>The other is this: The Prince having by ſome intelligence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that one Mrs. <hi>Treagle</hi> of <hi>Taunton</hi> had ſome Plate of Sir <hi>Samuel Rolles</hi> in her cuſtody, he ſent Sir <hi>Samuel Caſwarth</hi> a Comiſh Gentleman for it, with an expreſſe to me, that I ſhould cauſe it to be delivered unto him, whereupon I ſent for Mrs. <hi>Treagle</hi> (whoſe huſband was at that time in the Parliaments Quarters) The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman at firſt would willingly have concealed the Plate, but Sir <hi>Sa. Caſworth</hi> urging much to have the Princes order obſerved, I praid her to fetch me the Plate, otherwiſe I would ſend for it my ſelfe: hereupon ſhe brought it unto me in a baſket, and as I did then judge it was worth about 100 <hi>l.</hi> which being ſet before Sir <hi>Sa. Caſwarth</hi> upon the Table, I prayed him to preſent my very humble ſervice to the Prince, and this requeſt; that he would command my ſervice in ſuch things as might be agreeable to my truſt and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119479:12"/>command, and that I might not be made inſtrumental in a ſervice of that nature, and I willed the woman to take back the Plate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and ſecure it according to her truſt. Mrs. <hi>Treagles</hi> Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny followeth.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="deposition">
               <body>
                  <p>I Frances Treagle, <hi>wife of</hi> George Treagle <hi>of</hi> Taunton, <hi>doe teſtifie that when Sir.</hi> John Stawell <hi>was Governour of</hi> Taunton, <hi>about the yeare of your Lord</hi> 1645. <hi>there came a Gentleman unto me, whoſe name I did afterwards underſtand was Sir</hi> Samuell Caſwarth, <hi>who told me, that he came by authority from Prince</hi> Maurice <hi>to demand ſuch Plate and Jewels, as Sir</hi> Samuel Rolle <hi>his Lady had left with me, whereupon I did uſe means to acquaint Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>therewith, who willed me to keep the plate which I had in my cuſtody, for he ſaw no cauſe why the ſame ſhould be delivered away, and thereupon the Gentleman was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed, and the plate preſerved, which I did afterwards ſend to</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, <hi>to Sir</hi> Samuel Rolle <hi>by one Mr.</hi> Budd <hi>of this Town. And this</hi> I <hi>am ready to teſtifie upon my oath, and have hereunto ſubſcribed my name the third day of</hi> October 1653.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>FRANCES TREAGLE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>I will not ſay that the Prince was herewith diſpleaſed, but it was not long after that <hi>I</hi> did receive this order of diſcharge, as followeth:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="order">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>For Sir</hi> John Stawell, <hi>Governour of</hi> Taunton:</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ALthough I cannot be ſatisfied that the Caſtle is tenable dgainſt a ſtrong ſiege, yet I would have it mann'd, and in order to that I would have you draw out of your Garriſon, a good Captaine, Lieutenant, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, with fourſcore men, to maintain the ſame, and to victuall it for three moneths, and the reſt of your Garriſon to be ſent to</hi> Bridgewater. <hi>You are to reſerve four pieces only of Canou, and to ſend the reſt with bullet to</hi> Bridgwater. <hi>And in reſpect (as I am informed) you have great ſtore of proviſions already in the Caſtle, I would have you after the victualling of the Caſtle for the ſaid fourſcore men for three moneths, to ſend the reſt of your ſtore to</hi> Bridgwater. <hi>I am Sir,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your loving friend, <hi>MAURICE.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the march toward <hi>Honington,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>June</hi> 15. <hi>eleven a clock.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I hold not the command of the fourſcore men fit for you.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> doe conceive it a very great vanity for any man to boaſt of his own good works, and ſhould, with reflection upon my ſelfe ſoon have reprehended what is now written, did not a neceſſity enforce me to ſay ſomething of the forementioned particulars; and as <hi>I</hi> have been governed through the whole courſe of my life by that divine rule and principle in humanity, <hi>Doe as you would be done unto;</hi> this being a law unto me, when no obligation or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb facs="tcp:119479:13"/>did reſt upon me, to ſerve ſuch who did in thoſe days differ in judgment with me; ſo let me beſeech you to favor me in like manner, and the rather for that the higheſt ſecurity the whole world affords is engaged for my Indempnity, of which <hi>I</hi> ſhall make no manner of doubt, when theſe ſhall have the happineſs rightly to inform you.</p>
            <p>After the diſcharge ſent me by the Prince, for the ſecurity of my perſon, I lived in the City of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and ſuch other Gariſons and places of ſtrength as were then in the late Kings hands: at length about <hi>June</hi> 1645, <hi>I</hi> came unto the City and Gariſon of <hi>Exeter,</hi> where <hi>I</hi> did abide, until ſuch time as the Parliaments Army, under the conduct of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> then General, came and layd ſiege unto it; And his Excellency ſummoning the Town, the Governor and his Councel of War did reſolve upon a <hi>Parley,</hi> and did bethink themſelves of ſuch terms and <hi>conditions</hi> as might be ſafe and honorable. Upon which <hi>Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners</hi> were aſſigned to treat with the Officers and Gentlemen commiſſionate for that purpoſe by the General; the concluſion of which Treaty was the ſeveral <hi>Conceſſions, Articles,</hi> and <hi>Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> which were by Order of Parliment printed and publiſhed, commonly known by the name of the Articles of <hi>Exeter,</hi> which were concluded and agreed upon the eighth of <hi>April,</hi> 1646. and were read and approved by the then Houſe of Commons the ſixth of <hi>May,</hi> 1646. and afterwards by both the Houſes of Lords and Commons the fourth of <hi>November,</hi> 1647. in theſe words.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>THe Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament do approve of the Articles of</hi> Exeter, <hi>and order this Approbation be publiſhed, to the end all people concerned may take notice thereof; And that the Committees, Judges, Officers, and other perſons concerned therein, do take notice thereof and obſerve the ſame, any Orders or Ordinances to the contrary notwithſtanding.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>By the 12 of the ſaid Articles it is agreed, That no Lords, Knights, Gentlemen, Clergymen, Chaplains, (excepting thoſe who are by name excepted by Parliament from Pardon and Compoſition) Officers, Citizens, and Souldiers, and all other perſons comprized in theſe Articles, ſhall be queſtioned or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable for any act paſſed by them done (or by any other done by their procurement) relating unto the unhappy Differences betwixt his Majeſty and the Parliament; they ſubmitting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to reaſonable and moderate Compoſition for their Eſtates, which the General Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> ſhall really endevor with the Parliament, that it ſhall not exceed two years value of any mans real eſtate reſpectively; and for perſonal, according to the ordinary rules, not exceeding the proportion aforeſaid: Which Compoſition being made, they ſhall have Indempnity for their perſons, and enjoy their Eſtates and all other Immunities, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119479:13"/>payment of any fifth or twentieth part, or any other Taxes or Impoſitions, except what ſhall be hereafter charged upon them in common with other Subjects of this Kingdom, by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parliament.</p>
            <p>By the 21 of the ſaid Articles it is agreed, That no Oath, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, Proteſtation, or Subſcription relating thereunto, ſhall be impoſed upon any perſon whatſoever compriſed within theſe Articles, but onely ſuch as ſhall binde all perſons aforeſaid, not to bear Arms againſt the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> now ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> nor wilfully to do any act prejudicial to their affairs, whileſt they remain in their Quarters; except the perſons afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſhall firſt render themſelves unto the Parliament, who ſhall cauſe them to be ſecured if they think fit.</p>
            <p>The 14 of <hi>April,</hi> 1646. the ſaid Lord General <hi>Fairfax</hi> gave a Certificate under his Hand and Seal, ſignifying that <hi>I</hi> was in the ſaid City at the ſurrender, and was to have the benefit of the Articles then agreed upon, which Certificate is in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="certificate">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ffer the Bearer hereof Sir</hi> John Stawell, <hi>Knight of the</hi> Bath, <hi>who was in the City of</hi> Exeter, <hi>and is to have the benefit of the Articles agreed unto by me at the time of the ſurrendering thereof, with his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Horſe, Arms, and Goods, to paſs quietly unto their ſeveral homes, and other parts in the Parliaments quarters, and from thence to</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, <hi>and to enjoy and diſpoſe of all his and their Goods, Debts and Movables (allowed by the Articles) during the ſpace of four Months next after the ninth of this inſtant</hi> April, <hi>without any interruption or moleſtation: And if he ſhall not make any Compoſition with the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment during that time, and ſhall be reſolved to depart the Kingdom within the ſaid four Months, to go into any part beyond the Seas.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given under my hand and ſeal at <hi>Exceſter,</hi> 
                        <date>the <hi>14</hi> day of <hi>April, 1646.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>FAIRFAX.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>To all Officers and Souldiers under my command, and all others whom it may concern.</trailer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The 15 of <hi>July,</hi> 1646. I came to <hi>London,</hi> and according to an Order of Parliament, of the ſecond of <hi>July,</hi> 1646. and within the time therein limited came before the Committee for the Militia, and there undertook, by a ſubſcription under my hand, not to bear Arms againſt the Parliament, according to the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſaid 21 Article, and the ſaid Order of Parliament; which Order, and the ſubſcription thereupon, follow in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="Parliamentary_order">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THat all perſons, of what degree or quality ſoever, compriſed within the Articles of</hi> Oxon, Exon, <hi>and all other Gariſons, that are already come to the Cities of</hi> London <hi>and</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>and places within the Lines of Communication, ſhall before Thurſday next, being the ninth day of this inſtant Month of</hi> July, <hi>repair to Guildhall,</hi> London, <hi>and ſhall there, in preſence of any three of the Committee of the Militia of
<pb facs="tcp:119479:14"/>the City of</hi> London, <hi>produce their Paſſes, and ſhall according to the Articles engage themſelves by promiſe, not to bear Arms againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, nor wilfully do any act prejudicial to their affairs, ſo long as they remain in their quarters. And that all perſons, of what degree or qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity ſoever, compriſed within any of the ſaid Articles, as ſhall hereafter come within the ſaid City and Lines of Communication, ſhall within four days after their coming repair to Guildhall,</hi> London, <hi>and ſhall there likewiſe produce their Paſſes, and make the like engagement. And the Committee of the Militia, or any three of them, are hereby authorized to receive the ſaid engagement, and take the reſpective ſubſcriptions of the perſons; and for this purpoſe are to ſit conſtantly three days in the week;</hi> viz. Mundays, Wedneſdays, <hi>and</hi> Fridays, <hi>between the hour of three and ſeven in the afternoon. And laſtly it is ordered, That ſuch of the perſons, comprized within any of the ſaid Articles, as ſhall neglect or refuſe to obſerve this Order, or do any thing contrary to the ſaid Articles, ſhall forfeit the benefit of the ſaid Articles: And this to be printed, and publiſhed by ſound of Trumpet and beat of Drum; and the Committee of the Militia of</hi> London <hi>is deſired to take care that this be ſo publiſhed accordingly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>HEN. SCOBELL, <hi>Cleric. Parliamenti.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="subscription">
               <body>
                  <head>The Subſcription is thus certified.</head>
                  <p>I Am commanded by the Committee of the Militia of <hi>London,</hi> to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie, That Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> did promiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid Committee, that he would not bear Arms againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor wilfully do any act prejudicial to their affairs, whiles he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in their Quarters; and thereunto ſubſcribed his name, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Order of Parliament in that behalf.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated at Guildhall, <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> 
                        <date>the <hi>18</hi> of <hi>July, 1646.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>ADAM BANCKES, Clerk <hi>to the ſaid Committee.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Mr <hi>Aſh</hi> having the next day after my coming to <hi>London</hi> given me a friendly viſit (as I then underſtood it) I did a day or two before I preſented my Petition to the Committee at <hi>Goldſmiths<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> where he was Chair-man, wait upon him at his Brothers Houſe in <hi>Fanchurch-ſtreet,</hi> and did acquaint him with my purpoſe to petition, and pray'd his furtherance therein: He did then make me acquainted with the day that the Committee ſat, at which time he would not fail to be there himſelf, and would in all friendly manner further my buſineſs: upon my return from him that night I drew up my Petition; and I had the favor of Mr <hi>Duke Stonehouſe,</hi> my Kinſman, who was then with me, and writes a better hand then my ſelf, to write it for me, which Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition followeth in theſe words.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:119479:14"/>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>For the Honorable the Committee for Compoſitions ſitting at Goldſmiths-Hall:</head>
                  <head type="sub">The Humble Petition of Sir <hi>John Stawell;</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>SHEWETH,</opener>
                  <p>THat your Petitioners Eſtate hath been for a long time ſequeſtred, and himſelf reduced to very great wants, which being ſupplied by the help of his Friends, hath added much to his former Debts and Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  <p>He humbly prays, That ye will be pleaſed to admit him to his Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, according to the Articles of <hi>Exeter,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax</hi> his Certiflcate, which renders him capable of that Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>And your Petitioner ſhall &amp;c.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The next day, being the 24 of <hi>July,</hi> Mr <hi>Stonehouſe</hi> did me the favor to accompany me to <hi>Goldſmiths-Hall;</hi> and when I came to the door where the Committee ſat, I deſired the Door-Keeper to acquaint Mr <hi>Aſh</hi> that I was without, and had a Petition to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver; who brought me this Anſwer, That as ſoon as Sir <hi>Henry Berkleyes</hi> buſineſs was over, I ſhould be the next: about half an hour after I was called for, and none admitted who were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out to come along with me: When I came in, I tendered my Petition to the Committee, and put it into Mr <hi>Aſh</hi> his hands, who when he had read it, threw it down upon the Table, and ſaid that it was a Remonſtrance, and not a Petition; and put it from him with his hand towards me, as far as he could reach, for me to receive it again: whereupon I told him that I had brought that for him, and for my ſelf I had a copy, and ſo left it there upon the Table. He told me that I muſt confeſs my Delinquency before I could be admitted to Compoſition: I told him that I came thither to compound for my Eſtate, and not to confeſs De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquency, for that my Articles did require no ſuch thing, and that by them my Delinquency was remitted. I did withall tell him, that I had born Arms for the King, and that I did ſo by his command; and I ſaid [by his command] not that I ſtood upon my juſtification, but to entitle me to the Articles of <hi>Exeter,</hi> which do excuſe me for acts done, relating unto the unhappy Differences. Then he asked me, if I had taken the Negative Oath and Covenant; I told him, no; whereupon he told me, that before I could be admitted to Compoſition, I muſt take them both: I replyed, that by my Articles I was freed from taking of any Oaths; and, I well remember, that preſſing upon me to take thoſe Oaths, and to acknowledge in my Petition my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquency, I made him at laſt this Anſwer; Mr <hi>Aſh,</hi> I have known you long, and my good Friend, and do deſire to preſerve you ſo; and for theſe Gentlemen that are of the Parliament (for I did not know then but that they had been ſo) there was very great reaſon that my judgment and opinion ſhould ſubſcribe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119479:15"/>unto theirs: but as for my Eſtate, it was my ſervant, and I had a power to command it; but my Conſcience was my maſter, and had power to command me, and to it I muſt yield obedience: and ſince thoſe Oaths, which you offer me, are contrary to my Articles, and repugnant to thoſe which formerly I have taken, I deſire you will excuſe me, if I refuſe them. Whereupon Mr <hi>Aſh</hi> willed me to withdraw; And being called for again, Mr <hi>Aſh</hi> told me that I was but lately come to Town, and it might be that I had not taken notice of the Negative Oath and Covenant, and therefore they would afford me ſome time to conſider of it; but my Anſwer was, that I did not deſire any time to conſider of what was a Right which did belong unto me by my Articles, and of which if I ſhould accept, and make them the ſame Anſwer now I do, they would ſay, that by the acceptation of time I had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed their expectations, which I was unwilling to do. Hereupon I was willed to withdraw, and did again attend without the door, until the Committee roſe, not knowing whether they might have any thing more to ſay unto me; but at that time heard nothing more from them, nor at any time after, until <hi>April</hi> 12. following, at which time I received a Ticket from a meſſenger ſent unto me, which was to appear the next day at <hi>Goldſmiths-Hall,</hi> at two of the clock in the afternoon: I did then appear, and I well remember that when I came into the room where the Committee ſat, Mr <hi>Aſh</hi> had left the Chair unto Mr <hi>John Stephens,</hi> and then told Mr <hi>Stephens</hi> that I had been formerly before them, and had prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Petition, deſiring to be admitted unto my Compoſition; but that I had refuſed both to confeſs my Delinquency by my Petition, and to take the Negative Oath and Covenant; and that the Committee had given me time till then to conſider of it: Whereupon Mr <hi>Stephens</hi> asked me, what I did ſay to it; I made him this Anſwer, That there was nothing in what Mr <hi>Aſh</hi> had delivered which had the nature of a queſtion to me, but was ſpoken to inform him, who was not there the day before: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto Mr <hi>Stephens</hi> replyed, <hi>Say you ſo? Then Sir, by your leave I will put you a ſhort queſtion; Will you take the Negative Oath and Covenant or no?</hi> To which I anſwered, that uſually Sir, to a ſhort queſtion I do return a ſhort anſwer; but Sir, I ſhall not do ſo unto you, but make you the ſame Anſwer which I made unto the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee the laſt time I was here; That I have the benefit of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of <hi>Exeter,</hi> which do exempt me from taking of Oaths; and in regard they are not agreeable to ſuch Oaths as I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly taken, I deſire to be excuſed: And this was all that did at that time paſs betwixt us. And hereupon they willed me to withdraw, and about half an hour after two of their meſſengers came to me as I was ſitting without the door, and ſhewed me a <hi>Mittimus,</hi> directed to the Sergeant at Arms, which followeth in theſe words.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:119479:15"/>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="writ">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>By the Committee for compounding with Delinquents,</hi> &amp;c. 13 Aug: 1646.</head>
                  <p>WHereas Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> was ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to appeare before this Committee, and there deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded whether he would take the Covenant, and Negative Oath, and he abſolutely refuſed to take either of them: Theſe are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by vertue of the Ordinances of Parliament, of the fifth of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill,</hi> 1645. and of the firſt of <hi>November,</hi> 1645. to require you to take into your cuſtody the perſon of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> for his ſaid refuſall, and him ſafely to keep till he conform himſelfe thereunto, and for ſo doing this ſhall be your Warrant.</p>
                  <trailer>To the Serjeant of the Houſe of Commons, or his Deputy.</trailer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>AFter I had ſeen and read the <hi>Mittimus,</hi> and found my ſelfe a priſoner, I deſired to ſpeak again with the Committee, and one of the Meſſengers ſignifying ſo much unto them, I was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and ſpake unto them, to this effect.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Gentlemen, I finde by your</hi> Mittimus <hi>that you have made me a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner: I had very little before left me but my liberty, my reall Eſtate ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been under ſequeſtration for a long time, and my perſonall little more then what you ſee. As long as I had my liberty I did communicate my wants unto my friends, and I have been helpt and relieved by them: But now that you have taken my liberty from me, I deſire you to conſider of ſome maintenance that may be neceſſary for me. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto which Mr.</hi> Stephens <hi>made anſwer, that my requeſt was very juſt and reaſonable, and that there ſhould be conſideration had of it; and Mr.</hi> Aſh <hi>told me, that though Mr.</hi> Stephens <hi>ſhould forget it, he would not; and ſo with my thanks unto them for that promiſe, I left them: In all which ſeverall times both of my firſt and ſecond coming before them, my behaviour was no otherwiſe then might become a modeſt man, and perſons of their place and quality, as is testified hereafter by the teſtimony of Gentlemen of honour and worth of the ſame Committee, and the rest: Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Committee made this order.</hi>
            </q>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="order">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>At the Committee for compouning, <date>
                           <hi>13</hi> of <hi>Aug: 1646:</hi>
                        </date> Goldſmiths Hall.</dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>SIr <hi>John Stawell</hi> appeared, and refuſed to take the Negative Oath, and Covenant.</p>
                  <p>Ordered that Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> report his carriage to the Houſe, and that he be committed to the Serjeant at Armes, and Mr. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phens</hi> to report his deſire for an allowance of maintenance.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>John Leech:</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> within few daies after makes his report, and it
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119479:16"/>may eaſily be gathered from a teſtimony under Mr. <hi>Aſh</hi> his hand, what it was, and from whom he received his inſtructions, being not preſent himſelfe the firſt time that I appeared before the Committee, as he doth confeſſe by his Depoſition taken in the high Court of Juſtice; which teſtimony of Mr. <hi>Aſh</hi> followeth in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="deposition">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THat I do not remember the preciſe day of the month when Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>firſt appeared before the Committee at</hi> Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths Hall; <hi>But this I well remember, that it was about foure daies before the foure moneths limited by the Articles of</hi> Exeter <hi>were expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That I do not remember the preciſe words contained in that paper, which Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>then preſented to the Committee for his Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but I do remember that the Committee did reject the ſaid paper, telling Sir</hi> John Stawell, <hi>that it was a Remonſtrance, not a Petition, wherein he rejected the Parliaments mercy offered him in the Articles, and did put a contempt upon the Authority of the Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That I do not remember the very words contained in the ſaid paper, and which Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>then ſpake at the delivery thereof unto the Committee; yet I do remember that the ſenſe and ſubstance of both was to this effect;</hi> viz.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>THat the Parliament had ſeiſed and ſequeſtred his Eſtate, or had taken it away by force, for doing his duty to the King, as by the Law, and ſeverall Oathes which he had taken, he was bound to do; and that he could not have his Eſtate again, unleſſe he gave that Committee money to redeem it. That he was a perſon in debt, and his debts were much increaſed ſince his Eſtate was taken from him by the Parliament, by which means he was diſabled to pay the Committee much money. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, if they could accept of what he could procure, he would then compound with them for the redemption of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</p>
                     <p>That the Committee did then adviſe Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto the Authority of Parliament, and to petition for his compoſition as others had done, and not to expoſe his perſon and his eſtate to the will and pleaſure of the Parliament, and not to reject their mercy contained in the Articles of Exeter, to which he had a right, in caſe he did ſubmit thereunto; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Committee adviſed Sir <hi>John Stawel</hi> to take further time of conſideration, hoping that at his next appearance he would be better adviſed, and yeild ſubmiſſion to the Authority of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and conform to the rules of that Committee.</p>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:119479:16"/>
                     <p>That when Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> next appeared before the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, which was about three daies after the foure moneths limited by the Exeter Articles were expired, inſtead of ſubmitting to the Committee as was expected, he was higher in his expreſſions then at the firſt; upon which the Committee, upon his refuſall of taking the Negative Oath, committed him to the cuſtody of the Serjeant at Armes, untill the whole matter and manner of Sir <hi>John Stawells</hi> behaviour ſhould be reported to the Parliament.</p>
                     <p>That in ſhort time afterward Mr. <hi>John Stephens,</hi> a Member of that Committee, did report the ſame unto the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and in that report informed the houſe that the opinion of that Committee was, that Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> had ſlighted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned the Authority of the preſent Parliament, and forfeited their mercy contained in the Articles of <hi>Exeter.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That the Parliament, upon this report made by Mr. <hi>Stephens,</hi> ordered Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> to be brought to the Bar, to heare and receive this charge, and the ſenſe of the Houſe thereupon.</p>
                     <p>That when Sir <hi>John Stawel</hi> came into the Houſe, being brought in by the Serjeant at Armes, he was told by the Speaker, that he was a Traytor, or a Delinquent, and therefore was required to kneele at the Bar; Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> made him ſome croſſe grum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling anſwer, what the words were I do not remember; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed: But the Speaker having three times required him to kneele, and Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> ſtill refuſing, the Serjeant at Armes was required to take him away, which he did accordingly, and thereupon the Speaker did not then give him his charge.</p>
                     <p>That Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> having contemned the Authority of Parliament, the Houſe committed him to <hi>Newgate</hi> as a Traytor, and in ſhorttime after, ordered that he ſhould be proceeded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt as a Traytor.</p>
                  </q>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>John Aſh.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This is a true Copy.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Tracy Pauncefote, <hi>Register</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>THeſe Contents were ſigned by Mr. <hi>Aſh,</hi> and ſent to the high Court of Juſtice as evidence againſt me, and are now remaining in the Court of Articles in the ſame individuall paper which he ſubſcribed. So that from hence it may eaſily be infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that all my wrongs and ſufferings have flowen from Mr. <hi>Aſh</hi> his conſtruction of my Petition to be a Remonſtrance, and that therein I had refuſed the Parliaments mercy, and put a contempt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119479:17"/>upon the Authority of Parliament: and from Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> his report, the ſubſtance of which he took upon credit, that it was the ſence of that Committee, that I had ſlighted and contemned the Authority of the preſent Parliament, and forfeited their mercy contained in the Articles of <hi>Exeter,</hi> Upon this no man but will ſay, that the Parliament had good cauſe to ſend for me to their Bar, and to queſtion me for my former Ingagements, ſince they were told that I was in contempt of their Authority, and had forfeited their mercy contained in the Articles, which were my onely ſecurity: And being brought unto the Lobby about nine of the clock in the morning, I was put into a little dark corner upon the left hand of the entring in of the outermoſt door, my two Keepers attending without the door, and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none to come in unto me, but Mr. <hi>Aſh;</hi> who during the time of my being there, which was betwixt nine and three in the afternoon, was with me foure or five ſeverall times, and ſeeming in all his diſcourſe very much to condole the ſadneſſe of my condition. I very well remember that the laſt time that he was with me, he ſpake to me in theſe words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maſter, you told me the other day when I was with you, that your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition would go hard with you for that Deans and Chapters lands are expoſed unto ſale, at tenyeers value, you having not money in your purſe to pay your compoſition, muſt ſell your Fee-ſimple lands according to that rate. If it pleaſe you for to take</hi> 4000 l. <hi>for</hi> Aubury, <hi>I will help you to a Chapman that ſhall give you the money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon I told him, that he did not offer me halfe that it coſt me; he told me that he did, for that I had told him that the purchaſe did ſtand me but in 8000 <hi>l.</hi> I told him that it ſtood me upon the point of 9000 <hi>l.</hi> ready money: But now I underſtand from whence all my troubles do ariſe, and of thoſe command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which God had made, he that did break the leaſt did break them all; and therefore in coveting what did belong to another, he was a very great ſinner. But I told him that herein I would befriend him, that however he might covet <hi>Aubury,</hi> yet I would promiſe him he ſhould never have it; whereupon Mr. <hi>Aſh</hi> reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nay, you were beſt to ſay that I ſpake to you for <hi>Aubury;</hi> if you do, I proteſt I will deny it: unto which I replyed, Sir, be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that if I ſhall think fit at any time to charge you with it, I will aver it with ſo much conſidence and truth, that you ſhall not dare to deny it; then he ſaid unto me, Sir, I perceive you grow angry, and it is time to leave you, and ſo went, as I ſuppoſe into the houſe: and within a quarter of an houre after I was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the Bar, which was upon the 18th day of <hi>August,</hi> 1646. And being commanded to kneele, I prayed, that before I recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved any mark of their diſpleaſure, I might know my offence; and was thereupon committed to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and proſecution was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to be made againſt me at the next Aſſiſes in <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119479:17"/>in the years 1647. &amp; 1648. and afterwards at the Upper Bench, as by theſe following Reſolves, and the Order for my Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, appears.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="court_order">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Die Martis</hi> 18. <hi>Auguſti</hi> 1646.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> being brought by the Serjeant to the Bar, and by Maſter Speaker commanded to kneel, refuſed, deſiring firſt to be informed what was his offence. He was thereupon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded preſently to withdraw.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="resolution">
               <body>
                  <p>Reſolved,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THat Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>be forthwith committed priſoner to</hi> New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate <hi>for High Treaſon for levying War againſt the Parliament. Ordered that the Sheriffs of</hi> London <hi>and</hi> Middleſex <hi>be required to take ſpecial care, That Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>committed by warrant of this Houſe Priſoner to</hi> Newgate <hi>for high Treaſon for levying war againſt the Parliament, be kept in ſure and ſafe cuſtody.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Upon which Order a <hi>Mittimus</hi> was drawn up under the Speakers hand, which followeth in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="writ">
               <body>
                  <p>BY Vertue of an Order of the Houſe of Commons, Theſe are to require you to receive from the Serjeant at Arms, or his Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Body of Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> Knight of the Bath into the Priſon of <hi>Newgate</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and him there to deteine in ſafe Custody as your Priſoner, until the pleaſure of the Houſe be ſignified to you to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; He being committed for High Treaſon for levying War againſt the Parliament: And for ſo doing this ſhall be your warrant,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>dated <date>18. Auguſti 1646.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>William Lenthall <hi>Speaker.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>To the Keeper of the Priſon of <hi>Newgate</hi> in <hi>London.</hi>
                  </trailer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="order">
               <body>
                  <p>Ordered,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THat Maſter</hi> Palmer, <hi>Maſter</hi> Walker, <hi>Maſter</hi> Harrington, <hi>Maſter</hi> Serle, <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Wroth, <hi>Maſter</hi> Blague, <hi>and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel</hi> Popham, <hi>or any two of them, doe take care that there be a Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and an Indictment prepared againſt Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>at the next Aſſiſes to be holden for the County of</hi> Somerſet <hi>for High Treaſon, for his levying War againſt the King, Parliament, and Kingdome of</hi> England.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:119479:18"/>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="order">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Die Lunae,</hi> 28 Feb. 1947.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Ordered,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THat Maſter</hi> Maynard, <hi>and Maſter</hi> Hill <hi>doe take care of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment againſt Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>at the next Aſſizes for</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="resolution">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Die Mercurii</hi> 14. <hi>Martii</hi> 1648.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REſolved by the Parliament, That Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>Knight be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt for life in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Bench.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Hen. Scobell Cler. Parliamenti.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And now having nothing left me to ſave either life or eſtate, but by way of Petition to make my cauſe knowne unto the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and having told Maſter <hi>Aſh</hi> when I came out from the Bar, that I hoped that in regard they did not admit me to ſpeak, they would not be diſpleaſed at my addreſs by petition: Upon this hint of my purpoſe, Maſter <hi>Aſh</hi> came unto me three or foure dayes (as I remember) after my commitment to <hi>Newgate:</hi> And after that he had expreſſed ſeemingly a great deal of ſorrow and trouble that his good Maſter (for ſo he called me) was in ſo ſad a condition, he offered me his ſervice to doe what poſſibly lay in his power; and ſithence there was nothing more ſeaſonable for me then good advice, he did earneſtly deſire me to apply my ſelfe very humbly to the Parliament by Petition. I told him that his advice &amp; my own reſolutions did very well agree, and that I did intend to doe ſo. Whereupon he told me that he had a very earneſt requeſt unto me, and prayed me that I would not deny it, which was, that he might have the honour to prefer my Petition for me; And if it were ſo that I would truſt him with it, if he did not give me a very ſpeedy account thereof, and that he did not uſe his utmoſt endeavors to accompliſh ſo much as I ſhould therein deſire, he would give me leave where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever I ſaw him, or ſpake of him, to ſay, <hi>My ſervant</hi> Aſh <hi>was an arrant knave.</hi> I told him, that although I did intend to deliver a Petition, yet it was not my purpoſe to have troubled him with it; but ſince he had ſo friendly invited me thereunto, he ſhould have it. He prayed me ſpeedily to draw it. I told him that I would. He told me then he would come the next morning to me for it, and accordingly he did ſo; but not liking the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for that I had expreſſed therein, That I had the benefit of the Articles of <hi>Exeter;</hi> and that I had accordingly ſubmitted unto my compoſition; and that I was refuſed only for denying to take the Negative Oath &amp; Covenant, and thereof re did pray that I might be referred unto my Compoſition, and reſtored to my Liberty. He told me that this Petition did too much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulate
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119479:18"/>with the Parliament (for ſo he termed it) that was highly diſpleaſed with me; and that I ſhould not petition in that way, but draw up an humble Petition, that ſhould ſhew that I was very ſorry that I had incurred their diſpleaſures in refuſing to kneele when they commanded me, and to excuſe that offence in the beſt manner that I could, and to beg their pardon for the ſame. And this he told me would be ſufficient to take off the Proſecution of my Indictment, which was the firſt thing in order to be done, the Aſſizes being ſo near at hand in the Countrey. Wherupon I ſent another Petition to him, which by his Letter written to me he ſeemed very well to approve of; but yet although I did very often ſollicit him by my Wife and Friends, to put him in minde to prefer the ſame, he never deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it to this day, nor did ever come neer me after that time: which Petition followeth in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Right Honourable the Commons aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in Parliament.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The Humble Petition of Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> Priſoner in <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WHereas your Petitioner by Command lately attended this Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſe, and being brought to the Bar, was enjoyned to kneel, which your Petitioner forbore to doe, not of any will to leſſen the great Reſpect and Reverence due to that Honourable Aſſembly, but conceiving he might firſt have ſpoken.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But now finding he hath committed an Error, for which he holds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf obliged to make an humble acknowledgement, and by this Petition to crave a favourable interpretation of his offence:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Your Petitioner humbly begs your pardon, being very ſorry that he hath given you ſo juſt cauſe of diſpleaſure, And ſhall account it, (in theſe his ſad misfortunes) a very great happineſs to be reſtored to a capacity of your favours, And that you would not look back upon what he prayes may be forgotten, but be pleaſed in the midſt of judgement to remember mercy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>And your Petitioner ſhall pray, &amp;c. <hi>John Stawell.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>But Maſter <hi>Aſh</hi> not willing to make me happy in the fruit of this Petition, inſomuch as the Parliaments former diſpleaſure according to the ſaid ſeverall Orders for my Indictment and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment for High Treaſon was put in execution upon me: And I was Indicted firſt at <hi>Taunton</hi> Aſſizes, where the Bill of high Treaſon was found; next at the Seſſions at <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> where there was an Ignoramus; and laſtly at <hi>Chard,</hi> where three In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictments,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119479:19"/>as I have heard, were found, one for High Treaſon, and two for Murther, for the killing of <hi>Oſborne</hi> at <hi>Marſhals Elme,</hi> and the other for the Execution of <hi>Viccary,</hi> when I was Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Taunton,</hi> many of the Grand Jury being the Inhabitants of <hi>Taunton,</hi> &amp; ſuch who had recovered judgments for great ſums of money againſt me, and have ſince purchaſed a good part of my Eſtate, which Indictments were afterwards removed by <hi>Certiorart</hi> into the then Kings Bench, where the 12. &amp; 13. of <hi>May</hi> 1649. I was Arraigned upon the indictment of High Treaſon, in levying war againſt the King upon the Statute of 25 <hi>E.</hi> 3. And upon my moving to plead ſpecially, the Court ordered accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly that I ſhould bring in my ſpecial pleading the firſt day of the next Term, and did aſſign me Counſel for that purpoſe. But I was never brought to plead further to that Indictment.</p>
            <p>The 18. of <hi>June</hi> 1649. An Act was printed &amp; publiſhed, Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>An Act for releif of all ſuch perſons as have been, or ſhal be ſued, moleſted, or any way dampnified, contrary to Articles or Conditions gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in time of War;</hi> In which Act Commiſſioners were nominated hear and determine Caſes concerning Articles according to the powers of the ſaid Act.</p>
            <p>Whereupon I did addreſs my ſelf to that Court by Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which was read the 10th. of <hi>July</hi> 1649. And was in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Right Honorable, the Lords, and others the Commiſſioners appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by an Act of Parliament for relief of ſuch as have been, are, or ſhall be ſued, moleſted, or any wayes dampnified, contrary to Articles or Conditions granted in time of War.</head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>The Humble Petition of Sir</hi> John Stawell, <hi>Priſoner in</hi> Newgate,</head>
                  <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                  <p>THat the Articles made upon the Surrender of <hi>Exeter,</hi> da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 8. <hi>Aprilis</hi> 1646, and a Paſs from the Lord Generall <hi>Fairfax,</hi> dated the 14th. of the ſame moneth (declaring accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to truth, that your Petitioner was compriſed in thoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles) he repaired to <hi>London</hi> to make his Compoſition, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to an Order of Parliament of the 2d. of <hi>July</hi> 1646. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired to the Committee of the Militia of <hi>London,</hi> within the time limited by that Order, and there undertook by a ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under his hand not to bear Armes againſt the Parliament, as by that Order, and the Intention of his Articles was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
                  <p>That the 24th. of the ſame Moneth of <hi>Iuly,</hi> he preferred a Petition in perſon to the Committee of <hi>Goldſmiths Hall</hi> for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119479:19"/>with Delinquents, deſiring to be admitted to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, according to the ſaid Articles, but was not admitted thereto, in regard he refuſed to take the Covenant and Negative Oath. And the 13th. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1646. was by Order of the ſaid Committee ſent Priſoner to <hi>Ely</hi>-Houſe for ſuch his refuſall.</p>
                  <p>That the 18th. of the ſame <hi>Auguſt</hi> he was ſent for as a Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent to the Bar of the Houſe of Commons, and was from thence committed to the Priſon of <hi>Newgate,</hi> during the pleaſure of that Houſe, for High Treaſon, in levying War againſt the Parl. All which will appear by true Copies annexed of the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> his Paſs, The Order of the ſecond of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1646. The Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate of the Clerk of the Committee of the Militia of <hi>London,</hi> The Petition to the Committee of <hi>Goldſmiths Hall,</hi> and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Warrants to the Serjeant at Arms, and Keeper of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Newgate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That during his impriſonment in <hi>Newgate,</hi> which hath been neer three years, he hath been indicted ſeverall times for Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and other crimes, and two ſeverall mornings arraigned for his life. And many Actions have been proſecuted againſt him, and Judgments had upon divers of the ſame, to the value of 6380 l. 10 s. A Schedule of which Actions is alſo hereunto annexed, and is threatned with many more. And all theſe for Acts done by him, relating unto the unhappy differences betwixt his late Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and the Parliament, before the date of the ſaid Articles, and his Eſtate continued all this time under Sequeſtration; whereby, and by waſte and ſpoile of his Woods and Timber, and taking away by the Committees in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> all that little of his goods which the Fate of War had left him, (and the Articles preſerved unto him) he hath ſuffered neere the loſs of 20000 l. in his Eſtate, beſide the hazards of his life by the aforeſaid Indictments, and what he hath ſuffered in his Liberty and Good name, which with good men is pretious and unvaluable.</p>
                  <p>That he hath not ſince the Articles granted unto him taken up Arms, or otherwiſe been ingaged in any new Hoſtility againſt the Parliament, or by his own default forfeited or loſt the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the ſaid Articles or Conditions thereby granted unto him, but hath in all things within his power conformed to the ſaid Articles, by ſubmitting to a reaſonable and moderate Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and a timely Petition to that purpoſe, and a Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Engagement not to bear Arms, or Act againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
                  <p>That by the 21. &amp; 22. of the ſaid Articles, No Oath, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, Proteſtation, or Subſcription relating thereunto, was to be impoſed upon him, but only ſuch as ſhould bind him not to bear Armes againſt the Parliament, and not wilfully doe any act prejudicial to their Affaires whileſt he remained in their Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119479:20"/>which your Petitioner hath punctually performed by his aforeſaid Subſcription before the Committee of the Militia of <hi>London,</hi> and hath really obſerved that Engagement.</p>
                  <p>That by the 12th. of thoſe Articles your Petitioner was not to be queſtioned or accountable for any Act paſt by him done, or by any other by his procurement relating unto the unhappy differences betwixt the late King and the Parliament; He ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to a reaſonable and moderate Compoſition for his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, which the Generall undertook to endeavour really with the Parliament, that it ſhould not exceed two years value of any mans reall Eſtate; and for perſonall, according to the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rules, not exceeding the proportion aforeſaid: which Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition being made, he was to have Indempnity of his Perſon, and enjoy his Eſtate and all other Immunities without payment of the fifth or twentieth part, or any other Taxes or Impoſitions, except what ſhould be hereafter charged upon him in Common with other Subjects of this Kingdome by Authority of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as by a Copy of the ſaid Articles hereto annexed may ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear.</p>
                  <p>That he humbly conceives that the preſſing of the Covenant and Negative Oath upon him in manner before expreſſed, and ſtop of his Compoſition for refuſall of the ſame, and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for that cauſe, and all the aforeſaid proceedings againſt him are contrary to the ſaid Articles, and the Conditions and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements of the Army made unto him: And he doth not conceive how the Orders of Parliament of the fifth of <hi>April,</hi> and the firſt of <hi>November</hi> 1645. mentioned in the Warrant of the Committee of <hi>Goldſmiths</hi> Hall, for their Authority, doth give them any power againſt your Petitioner, who came in by Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles upon the faith of the Army, and the Generals Paſs declaring ſo much, and thoſe Articles approved and confirmed by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, 6. <hi>May</hi> 1646. being in time after the ſaid Orders of the fifth of <hi>April,</hi> and firſt of <hi>November</hi> 1645. were made.</p>
                  <p>That according to the ſaid Act, he humbly prayes you will be pleaſed to appoint a ſpeedy time for the hearing of the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners complaint, and that the Keeper of the Priſon of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> may by your Order bring your Petitioner then before you, and ſuch cauſes as are againſt him for his Commitment and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teiner in that Priſon.</p>
                  <p>That your Petitioner by your Order may be freed of his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid impriſonment, and from all Votes, Indictments, Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Judgements, and Executions againſt him, for the matters before mentioned, and that ſatisfaction may be acknowledged upon the ſaid Judgements.</p>
                  <p>That he may be reſtored to the preſent poſſeſſion of all his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, without taking of Oathes or Covenant, and be freed from
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119479:20"/>Sequeſtration, in regard the profits of his Lands, the benefit made of his Woods and Timber, beſides his other loſſes, have been received and imployed to the uſe of the Parliament neer three yeares ſince his Petition for Compoſition was preferred, which far exceeds two yeares value of his Eſtate (which was the utmoſt penalty the ſaid Articles charged upon him for a Compoſition.</p>
                  <p>That all ſuch Goods as have been taken from him by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Committee, Sequeſtrators, and others, contrary to the Articles granted unto him, and ſince the Date of them, may be reſtored either in <hi>Specie,</hi> or in value, according to the equity of the ſaid Act.</p>
                  <p>That by your Order a ſtop may be given to all proceedings, hereafter to be had or proſecuted againſt him for any act by him done, or any other by his procurement relating unto the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy differences betwixt the late King and the Parliament; And that for the proſecution of his Complaint, he may (as in Caſes of like nature, have liberty upon Bayle to attend and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his buſineſs from time to time whileſt it depends before you. By all which, the Faith of the Army will be preſerved and vindicated, and your Honours and Juſtice will appear to a languiſhing Priſoner.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>John Stawell.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Upon this Petition no proceedings were made by that Court, whoſe Authority determining by the ſaid Act, The 10th. day of <hi>June,</hi> 1650. the ſame was renewed by Act of Parliament for ſix moneths, and then ended by expiration onely.</p>
            <p>The 20th day of <hi>March,</hi> 1650. the high Court of Juſtice was eſtabliſhed, and the 9th. day of <hi>July</hi> following, there was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed a ſpeciall Act for tryall of me, amongſt others, for my life before the high Court; It being therein declared, that I was a perſon not admitted to compoſition.</p>
            <p>The 20. of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1650. I was by order of the ſaid high Court re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from <hi>Newgate</hi> to the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> in order to my tryal.</p>
            <p>Tueſday the 17th. of <hi>December,</hi> 1650. I was brought to the Bar of the high Court of Juſtice, and a charge of high Treaſon exhibited againſt me, which followeth in theſe words:</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:119479:21"/>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="indictment">
               <body>
                  <head>A Charge of high Treaſon, Murther, Felony, and other high Crimes and Offences exhibited to the high Court of Juſtice, by <hi>Edmund Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux,</hi> Eſquire, Attorney Generall of the Common-wealth of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for and on the behalfe of the Keepers of the liberty of <hi>England</hi> by Authority of Parliament, againſt Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> alias <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> late of <hi>Higham</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> Knight of the Bath, by him perpetrated and committed; that is to ſay.</head>
                  <p>THat he the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> alias <hi>Stowell,</hi> out of a trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and wicked deſign to deſtroy the Parliament and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England,</hi> and to ſubvert the fundamentall lawes and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of this Nation, hath ſeverall times in ſeverall yeers of our Lord, one thouſand ſix hundred forty two, one thouſand ſix hundred forty three, one thouſand ſix hundred forty foure, one thouſand ſix hundred forty five, and one thouſand ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred forty ſix, in divers and ſundry places trayterouſly and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly levied and proſecuted a cruell and bloody war in this Land, on the behalfe of <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> late King of <hi>England,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament and the Forces raiſed by authority of the ſame; and hath been voluntarily aiding and aſſiſting to the ſaid late King &amp; his party in the late wars againſt the Parliament and people of <hi>England,</hi> and the forces raiſed by authority of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And particularly he the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> alias <hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> on the firſt day of <hi>March,</hi> in the yeer of our Lord one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred forty and two, did in an hoſtile manner at, or neer a place called <hi>Marſhalli Elme</hi> in the ſaid County of <hi>Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet,</hi> with many armed men horſe and foot, rebelliouſly and trayterouſly levie actuall war againſt the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and did with the ſaid war-like Forces commit divers and ſundry Murthers, Outrages, Cruelties, Burnings, and Deſtructions, upon the perſons, goods, houſes, and eſtates of divers of the people of <hi>England;</hi> and he the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> alias <hi>Stowell,</hi> at the time and place laſt before mentioned, and divers other times and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces did with the ſaid war-like Forces trayterouſly levie war, fight, and joyn battell againſt the Forces of the Parliament and people of <hi>England;</hi> In which ſaid fight, or fights, battell, or bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, he the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> alias <hi>Stowell,</hi> with the ſaid war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Forces did trayterouſly and maliciouſly kill, ſlay, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther many of the people of <hi>England;</hi> and particularly on the ſaid firſt day of <hi>March,</hi> in the ſaid yeer of our Lord one thouſand ſix hundred forty two, at <hi>Marſhals Elme</hi> aforeſaid, did trayterouſly, feloniouſly, and of his malice forethought, kill, ſlay, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther one <hi>Robert Oſeborne,</hi> late of <hi>Taunton</hi> in the ſaid County of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet</hi> Gentleman, and divers others: And further, that he the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> alias <hi>Stowell,</hi> the laſt day of <hi>Aprill,</hi> in the yeer of our Lord one thouſand ſix hundred forty and foure, at,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119479:21"/>or neer the Town of <hi>Taunton</hi> in the ſaid County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> feloniouſly and of his malice forethought, did kill and murther one <hi>Christopher Viccary,</hi> late of <hi>Taunton</hi> aforeſaid, in the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> Yeoman. All which Treaſons, Murthers, Felonies, Crimes, and Offences of him the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> alias <hi>Stowell,</hi> were and are againſt the publike peace, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and people of <hi>England.</hi> And the ſaid Attorney Generall by proteſtation ſaving to himſelfe, on the behalfe of the ſaid Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the liberty of <hi>England,</hi> Liberty of exhibiting at any time hereafter any other charge againſt the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> alias <hi>Stowell:</hi> And alſo of replying to the anſwers which he the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> alias <hi>Stowell</hi> ſhall make to the premiſſes, or any of them, or to any other charge that ſhall be ſo exhibited, doth for the ſaid Treaſons, Murthers, Felonies, Crimes, and Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, on the behalfe of the ſaid Keepers of the liberty of <hi>England,</hi> impeach the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> alias <hi>Stowell,</hi> as a Traytor, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer, Felon, and publike enemy to the Parliament and people of <hi>England;</hi> and prayeth that he may be put to anſwer all and ſingular the premiſſes, that ſuch Examinations, Tryals, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and Judgment may be thereupon had, as ſhall be agreeable to Juſtice:</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Edmund Prideauxs.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>To which I pleaded,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That I was not lyable to that Charge read againſt me by the ſaid Act directing my tryall; being a perſon admitted to Compoſition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That by the Articles of <hi>Exeter</hi> confirmed by Parliament, I ought not to be queſtioned for the offences laid to my charge.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the ſaid high Court gave me leave to plead the ſaid ſpeciall matter; and if that ſhould have fallen out againſt me, They likewiſe gave me liberty to plead the generall Iſſue: and after many daies ſolemne hearing and debate thereupon, the ſaid high Court did not think fit to proceed to Sentence, but to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie my caſe to the Parliament, which Certificate was in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Tueſday the</hi> 6th <hi>of</hi> May, 1651.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <head>To the ſupream Authority the Parliament of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IN obedience to an Act of this preſent Parliament,</hi> 9 July, 1650. <hi>This Court hath proceeded in the tryall of Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>for Treaſon and other offences, and upon hearing all the evidences and witneſſes
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119479:22"/>produced on the behalfe of the Common-wealth, and of the Priſoner; It was agreed by the whole Court that he was guilty of the Treaſon and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther high Crimes and Offences charged on him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But upon his ſpeciall pleading of right to the Articles of <hi>Exeter</hi> (confirmed by Parliament) by which no perſon therein compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſubmitting to reaſonable compoſition for their Eſtates, ſhould be queſtioned, or accountable for any Act paſſed by them done, relating to the unhappy differences.</p>
                  <p>The Court findeth that the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> was compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed within the ſaid Articles, and that in purſuance thereof he did ſubſcribe before a Committee for the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to an order in Parliament of the ſecond of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1646. And did alſo perſonally appeare within foure moneths after the ſaid Articles, and preſent a Petition to the Committee of <hi>Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths Hall</hi> for compoſition in relation to the ſaid Articles of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this Court conceiveth, and hath ſo reſolved and declared upon ſeverall debates, that his tender of that Petition (in the manner proved before this Court) was a ſubmiſſion to compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, according to the ſaid Articles of <hi>Exeter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But becauſe we finde ſome Reſolves of Parliament, that (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſaid Articles and his ſubmiſſion as aforeſaid) do order that he ſhould be tryed for Treaſon; And the ſaid Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for his preſent tryall doth declare him not admitted to compoſition: We therefore do not proceed to Sentence, but do thus humbly certifie his caſe to this honourable Parliament.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>At the high Court of Iuſtice in the Painted Chamber,</hi> 
                        <date> the 29th. <hi>of</hi> Aprill, 1651.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Richard Keeble,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Francis Thorpe,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iohn Green,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Rowe,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Steele,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iohn Sadler,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iohn Harriſon,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderwood,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Cooke,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Samuel Sheffeild,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iohn Hurſt.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Georg Manley,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iohn Blackwell,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iohn Parker,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Ayres,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Owen Rowe,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Cornelius Cooke,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Berners,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Samuel Moyer,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Weston,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Stone,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Georg Langham,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Nathaniel Whetham.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:119479:22"/>
            <p>This Certificate was incloſed in a Letter to Mr. Speaker, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the 29th. of <hi>Aprill,</hi> 1651.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Tueſday 6th. of <hi>May,</hi> 1651</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <head>For the right honourable the Speaker of the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe high Court of Justice at their meeting upon the buſineſſe of Sir John Stawell, who stands referred to them by the Parliament to be tryed, which have held ſeverall debates which have produced the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult contained in the paper incloſed; And it is our deſire it may be by you humbly preſented to the Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Painted Chamber, <date>6th. <hi>Maii,</hi> 1651.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     <signed>Your moſt humble Servants.<lb/>Signed by the ſame hands as are to the aboveſaid Certificate.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And the ſaid Certificate was read in Parliament the 10th. of <hi>Iune,</hi> 1651.</p>
            <p>The 16th. of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1651. my Eſtate was adjudged by Act of Parliament to be ſold, and my name accordingly inſerted in that Act for ſale, intituled an Act for ſale of Lands and Eſtates forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Common-wealth for Treaſon.</p>
            <p>In <hi>February</hi> after the paſſing of this Act I did addreſſe my ſelfe unto the Parliament by Petition, for my reliefe, which I put into Mr. <hi>Garlands</hi> hands, and followeth in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Supream Authority the Parliament of the Common-wealth of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">The humble Petition of Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> Priſoner in the Tower.</head>
                  <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THat your Petitioner was compriſed within the Articles of</hi> Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>and was to enjoy thoſe benefits which were agreed on at the rendition thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That he hath really performed all things within his power, which were by the ſaid Articles required on his part. Notwithſtanding he hath for the ſpace of almoſt ſix yeers lain under the weight of your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſures,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119479:23"/>not onely by the ſequeſtration of his Eſtate, and a long and ſad Impriſonment, but by the proſecution of his life upon ſeverall Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and laſtly, by a tryall before the high Court of Juſtice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Your Petitioner humbly praies that you will be pleaſed to cast your eye upon the annexed Certificate of that high Court directed unto you, and that as by the bleſſing of God, the Juſtice of that honourable Court, and the benefit of the ſaid Articles his life hath been hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to preſerved, ſo the liberty of his perſon and the poſſeſſion of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate may be granted unto him by the mediation of your favours, diſcharged of ſuch Iudgments, Sales, or Incumbrances, as are contrary to the intent and true meaning of the ſaid Articles, in regard that the profits of his Lands, the benefit made of his Woods and Timber, beſides his other loſſes, have been received and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the uſe of the Common-wealth, neer ſix yeers ſince his Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for Compoſition was preferred, which far exceeds two yeers va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of his Estate, which was the utmoſt penalty the ſaid Articles charged on him for a Compoſition.</p>
                  <p>Lastly, though principally intended, he humbly praies that himſelfe, together with his two Sons, <hi>John Stawell,</hi> and <hi>Edward Stawell,</hi> may be reſtored to your favours and good opinions, having not act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any thing to your diſservice ſince the date of the ſaid Articles. And however though ſome unhappy miſtakings when he firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred his Petition for Compoſition, have been the occaſion of all his ſufferings, yet he hopes the effects of them will not be permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in your wiſdome and Iuſtice abſolutely to ruine him.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>And your Petitioner ſhall ever pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> John Stawell.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>THe 29th. of <hi>September,</hi> 1652. an Act was printed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, entitled an Act for renewing of a former Act for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of perſons upon Articles, and Commiſſioners nominated therein for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>At the time of the paſſing of this Act, there were tendred two <hi>Proviſoes,</hi> the one of the 28th. of <hi>September,</hi> 1652. the other the day following, which were in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="proviso">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Tueſday the</hi> 28th. <hi>September,</hi> 1652.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <head type="sub">An Act for reviving a former Act for reliefe of perſons up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Articles, was this day read the third time.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Proviſo</hi> was tendred to this Act in theſe words; viz. <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that this Act, or any thing therein contained, ſhall not extend,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119479:23"/>nor be construed to extend to prejudice, alter, or make void any reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, votes, or judgments given in the Parliament touching any the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles aforeſaid, or any perſons claiming thereby.</hi> Which <hi>Proviſo</hi> was read the firſt and ſecond time, and the Queſtion being put that this <hi>Proviſo</hi> be part of this Act, it paſſed in the Negative: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved that the <hi>Proviſo</hi> be rejected.</p>
                  <closer/>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>Vera Copia.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Henry Scobell <hi>Clerk of the Parliament.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="proviso">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Wedneſday the</hi> 29th. <hi>of</hi> September, 1652:</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <head type="sub">The houſe reſumed the debate upon the Bill for reviving the former Act for reliefe of perſons upon Articles.</head>
                  <p>ANother <hi>Proviſo</hi> was tendred to this Bill in theſe words. <hi>Provided alwaies and be it hereby enacted and declared, that no reall or perſonall Eſtate which hath been ſetled, conveyed, or aſſured to any perſon, or perſons, by vertue of any Act, Ordinance, or Order of this preſent Parliament ſhall be made null, vacated, or otherwiſe determined or diſpoſed of by the Commiſſioners named in this Act, or by their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but that if they ſhall ſee cauſe of reſtitution by vertue of Articles ſubject unto their Cognizance, they make a Ward not in</hi> Specie <hi>againſt the particular perſon or perſons upon whom ſuch Eſtate or Eſtates be ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, conveyed, or aſſured, but in value to be ſatisfied by ſuch other Lands or Revenew, as the Parliament ſhall direct any, thing in this Act, or the former which is hereby revived, to the contrary notwithſtanding.</hi> And the Queſtion being put, that the <hi>Proviſo</hi> be read a ſecond time, It paſſed with the Negative.</p>
                  <closer/>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>Vera Copia.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Henry Scobell <hi>Clerk of the Parliament.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>BUt theſe <hi>Proviſoes,</hi> tending to the limitation of that benefit which the houſe was moſt honourably pleaſed to grant and allow to ſuch perſons as ſhould claim reliefe by Articles, were both rejected: And it was reſolved upon the Queſtion in the Negative; which I humbly pray may be ſpecially obſerved.</p>
            <p>The 14th. of <hi>October</hi> following, I exhibited my Petition to the ſaid Court, which followeth in theſe words.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:119479:24"/>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Honourable the Commiſsioners for reliefe upon Articles of War.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The humble Petition of Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> Priſoner in the Tower,</head>
                  <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THat he was in the Garriſon of the City of</hi> Exeter, <hi>and was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed in the Articles made the</hi> 8th. <hi>of</hi> April 1646. <hi>and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards confirmed by the Parliament for the ſurrender of the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That by the</hi> 12th. <hi>of the ſaid Articles it was agreed, that no perſon compriſed in the ſaid Articles, excepting thoſe who were by name exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted by Parliament from pardon and compoſition (under which excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he was not) ſhall be queſtioned or accomptable for any Act paſſed by them done, or any other done by their procurement, relating unto the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy differences betwixt the late King and the Parliament, they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting themſelves to reaſonable and moderate Compoſition for their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, which the then Generall Sir</hi> Thomas Fairfax <hi>was really to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour with the Parliament that it ſhould not exceed two years value of any mans reall eſtate reſpectively; and for perſonal, according to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary rules, not exceeding the proportion aforeſaid; which Compoſition being made, they ſhould have indempnity for their perſons, and enjoy their estates and all other immunities without payment of</hi> 5th. <hi>or</hi> 20th. <hi>part, or any other Taxes or Impoſitions, except what ſhould hereafter be charged upon them in common with other Subjects by authority of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That by the</hi> 21th. <hi>Article it was further agreed, That no Oath, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, Proteſtation, or Subſcription relating thereunto, ſhall be impoſed upon any perſon whatſoever compriſed within the ſaid Articles, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch as ſhall binde all perſons aforeſaid not to beare Armes, or Act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Parliament of</hi> England <hi>ſitting at</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>or willfully doe any Act prejudiciall to their affaires whilest they remain in their Quarters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That he had a Certificate under the hand and ſcale of the then Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, dated the</hi> 14th. <hi>day of</hi> April 1646. <hi>ſignifying that he was in the ſaid City at the time of the ſurrendring thereof, and was to have the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of thoſe Articles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That upon the</hi> 15th. <hi>day of</hi> July 1646. <hi>he came to the City of</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, <hi>to make his Compoſition, and according to an Order of Parliament of the</hi> 2d. <hi>of</hi> July 1646. <hi>repaired to the Committee of the</hi> Militia <hi>of</hi> London <hi>within the time limited by the ſaid Order, and before them undertook by a ſubſcription under his hand not to beare Armes or act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament, as by that Order and the intention of the ſaid</hi> 21th. <hi>Article was required.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That upon the</hi> 24th. <hi>of the ſame moneth of</hi> July <hi>he preferred his Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition in perſon to the Committee of</hi> Gold-Smiths <hi>Hall for compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Delinquents, deſiring to be admitted to his Compoſition accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119479:24"/>to the ſaid Articles; But was not admitted thereunto in regard he refuſed to take the Covenant and Negative Oath; And on the</hi> 13th. <hi>day of</hi> Auguſt 1646. <hi>was by Order of the ſaid Committee, for ſuch his refuſall only, committed to the cuſtody of the Sergeant at Armes, and kept priſoner in</hi> Ely <hi>Houſe; And on the</hi> 18th. <hi>day of the ſame</hi> Auguſt <hi>being ſent for as a Delinquent before the Houſe of Commons, was from thence committed to the priſon of</hi> Newgate <hi>during the pleaſure of the Houſe for high Treaſon, and levying of war againſt the Parliament, where he continued priſoner almoſt for the ſpace of four years before his remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall to the Tower.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That during his Impriſonment in</hi> Newgate <hi>he hath been indicted ſeveral times for Treaſon and other crimes, and two ſeveral mornings ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned for his life at the then Kings Bench Barr; And many Actions have been proſecuted againſt him, and Iudgments had upon divers of them, to the value of neer</hi> 7000 <hi>l. in damages; And all theſe for Acts done by him relating to the late unhappy differences betwixt the late king and the Parliament, and before the date of the ſaid Articles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That in</hi> July 1650. <hi>he was by Order of the High Court of Iuſtice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from</hi> Newgate <hi>to the</hi> Tower <hi>of</hi> London, <hi>and there kept in cloſe cuſtody for ſome moneths; And on the</hi> 17th. <hi>day of</hi> December 1650. <hi>and divers dayes after brought before the ſaid High Court, and tryed for his life, and after many dayes tryal, the examination of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Witneſſes, and a very ſtrict ſearch and enquiry into all actions, and the performance of the Articles on his part, the ſaid High Court did not think fit to proceed to ſentence, but to certifie the Parliament of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, as by the Copy of the ſaid Certificate hereunto annexed may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That ever ſince the ſaid Tryal he hath continued priſoner in the</hi> Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>and from the time of granting the ſaid Articles (being almost ſeven years ſince) his estate hath been kept under Sequeſtration, whereby, and by the encreaſe of his Debts, the waſte and felling of his Woods and Tym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and ſpoyling his Houſes, and the taking away of all that little that the War had left him, and which was by the ſaid Articles preſerved unto him, He hath ſuffered the loſse of neere</hi> 30000 l. <hi>in his eſtate, out of which he hath not been allowed any thing towards his ſubſiſtance, beſides what he hath ſuffered by a ſad and tedious Impriſonment, and hazard of his life by the aforeſaid Indictments and Proſecutions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That by an Act of Parliament paſsed on the</hi> 16th. <hi>of</hi> July 1651. <hi>his Eſtate amongſt divers others was declared and adjudged to be forfeited by him for Treaſon againſt the Parliament, and the ſame hath been ſince ſold accordingly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That he hath not (neither any of his ſonnes or Servants have) ſince the granting of the ſaid Articles, taken up Armes, or otherwiſe been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in any Act of hostility againſt the Parliament, neither hath he by any default of his forfeited or loſt the benefit of the ſaid Articles, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions granted unto him, but hath in all things within his power con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119479:25"/>to the ſaid Articles, by ſubmitting to Compoſition in due time, and by a ſubſcription and Engagement not to bear Armes, or Act againſt the Parliament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherefore your Petitioner humbly prayes, that you will be pleaſed to caſt your eves upon the annexed Certificate of the High Court of Juſtice, atteſted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Maſter</hi> Scobells <hi>hand: And that, as by the bleſſing of God, the Juſtice of that Honourable Court, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the ſaid Articles, his life hath been hither unto preſerved, ſo the Liberty of his perſon, and the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of his eſtate may be granted unto him, diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of ſuch Judgements, Sales, Executions, or Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances, as are contrary to the intent and true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſaid Articles; And alſo that by the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your favours, he may enjoy his Eſtate free from Compoſition, in regard that the profits of his Lands, the benefit made of his Wood and Timber, and much of his other Loſſes, have been received and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied to the uſe of the Common-wealth almoſt ſeven years ſince his Petition for Compoſition was prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which farre exceeds two years value of his Eſtate (which was the utmoſt penalty the ſaid Articles char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on him for a Compoſition;) And if this his hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble requeſt ſhall not finde favour in your ſight, Then he further prayes, that he may receive from this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Committee ſuch juſtice and right as ſhall be agreeable to his Articles, and the ſeveral Acts of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament eſtabliſhed for his reliefe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>And your Petitioner ſhall,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>To this Petition the Counſell for the Common-wealth atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſaid Court, and the Counſell for the Truſtees for Sale of Delinquents Lands, put in their ſeverall Demurrers, which follow in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="demurrer">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Plea and Demurrer of</hi> Edmund Prideaux, <hi>Eſquire, Attorney Generall for the Common-wealth of</hi> England, <hi>to the Petition of Sir</hi> John Stawell.</head>
                  <p>THe ſaid Attorney Generall (not confeſſing any the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the ſaid Petition contained to be true, in ſuch manner and forme as the ſame are therein ſet forth; The whole Scope of the ſaid Petition of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119479:25"/>to ſeek releife upon the Articles made the eighth of <hi>April</hi> 1646. upon the Surrender of <hi>Exeter;</hi> (within which Articles, as by the ſaid Petition is ſuppoſed, he the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> was and is compriſed) as to the Liberty of his Perſon, and Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of his Eſtate) for Plea thereunto ſaith, That inaſmuch as in and by the ſaid Petition it doth appeare that he the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell was committed by the Houſe of Commons</hi> (thereby mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) as is conceived) the Commons of England aſſembled in Parlia.) <hi>to the Priſon of Newgate, during the pleaſure of the Houſe</hi> (ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by again meaning) as is alſo conceived) the ſaid Commons of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland aſſembled in Parliament) <hi>for High Treaſon in levying war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament:</hi> And for that it alſo appeareth in and by the ſaid Petition, <hi>That by an Act of Parliament paſſed the ſixteenth day of</hi> July 1651. <hi>The Eſtate of the ſaid Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>(amongst divers others) was declared and adjudged to be by him forfeited for High Treaſon againſt the Parliament; And the ſaid Eſtate ſo adjudged forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, hath been ſince ſold and diſpoſed of, in purſuance, and by vertue and authority of the ſaid Act of Parliament:</hi> Thereupon the ſaid Attorney Generall doth demurre in Law upon the ſaid Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and doth demand the judgement of this Court, if this Court hath Jurisdiction, or may or ought to hold Plea, or take conu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of the ſaid matters in the ſaid Petition contained; And the rather for that it doth not appear in or by the ſaid Petition, that the ſaid Commons of England aſſembled in Parliament have declared their pleaſure as touching the impriſonment of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> for the Treaſon aforeſaid; And the Parliament of England having by the aforeſaid Act (in which all the people of England, and their conſents thereunto, are involved and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded) adjudged the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> to have forfeited his Eſtate for High Treaſon, and for that the ſame is forfeited as aforeſaid; And the ſaid Judgement being now fully executed, and the Eſtate of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> in fact ſold and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of by, and according to the ſaid Act of Parliament; The ſaid Attorney Generall further ſaith, That no Subordinate, or Delegated Court or Authority whatſoever, hath power to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the cauſe of the aforeſaid Judgement; Nor is the ſaid Judgement to be reverſed or annulled, but by immediate pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and authority of Parliament, and is not, nor can be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to any other Judicature whatſoever; Nor can, nor ought it to be ſuppoſed that the aforeſaid Judgement is or hath been given in breach or violation of any Articles confirmed by Parliament, in the obſervation, or violation of which Articles, the Faith of the Army, and Honour and Juſtice of the Nation of England is ſo highly concerned; Neither ought this Court (as the Attorney Generall humbly offereth) to admit the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Act of Parliament, and the proceedings thereupon had, to be drawne into examination; for that were to ſit in Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119479:26"/>upon the Parliament, and to judge their Actions; For all which Cauſes, and other apparent inſufficiencies and imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in the ſaid Petition contained, the ſaid Attorney General doth likewiſe demur in Law, and doth demand judgment of the Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, if any further proceedings ſhall be had upon the ſaid Petition, as to the impriſonment of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> and the reſtitution unto him of his Eſtate ſo forfeited by him, and ſold and diſpoſed of as aforeſaid, or any part thereof.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline> Delivered into the Court by Mr. <hi>Hurſt</hi> 
                        <date>the 10th. of <hi>Novem.</hi> 1652.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Edmund Prideaux,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Tho: Widdrington,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iohn Green,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Barth. Hall,</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iohn Hurſt.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>A true Copy</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Tracy Pauncefote</hi> Regiſtr. </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="demurrer">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Honourable the Commiſſioners for Releife upon Articles in time of Warre.</head>
                  <p>WHereas by your Orders of the ſixth and tenth of <hi>Novem.</hi> inſtant, the Truſtees appointed by Act of parliament of the ſixteenth of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1651. for Sale of Eſtates forfeited to the Common-wealth for Treaſon, were to ſhew cauſe in writing why all further proceedings touching the Sale of Sir <hi>Iohn Stowells</hi> Eſtate (if any thing remain to be done concerning the ſame) ſhould not be ſtayed till further order and direction from you.</p>
                  <p>In anſwer whereunto by their Counſell, they return this for cauſe, That by the aforeſaid Act of Parliament, the Eſtate of Sir <hi>John Stowell</hi> amongſt others is declared and adjudged to be juſtly forfeited by him for his Treaſon againſt the Parliament &amp; Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England,</hi> and is thereby veſted and ſetled in the ſaid Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees and their heires in order to be ſold for the benefit of the Common-wealth: That accordingly and in purſuance of their truſt they have ſold all Sir <hi>John Stowells</hi> eſtate; ſome part to the tennants themſelves (who thereby have drowned their eſtates) other parts to others upon doubling their Publick faith Bills, &amp; moſt of the Purchaſers are in poſſeſſion. That this being done by Act and Authority of Parliament, ought not (as they humbly conceive) to be queſtioned or reverſt by any derivative Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity whatſoever. And therefore the ſaid Truſtees do demurre in Law, and pray the Judgement of this Court, if this Court hath Juriſdiction, or may hold Plea of this cauſe: For Plea they ſay, that by the laſt proviſo in your Act, power is given you to ſtay ſale of eſtates of ſuch perſons as have not Articles confirmed by Parliament, whereas the Articles which Sir <hi>John Stowell</hi> claimes benefit of, are confirmed, as in his Petition is alledged.</p>
                  <p>They further ſay, for that it appeares that the firſt Act autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119479:26"/>this Court to give relief upon Articles, did determine the twentieth of <hi>June</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred and fifty, and that the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> by an Act paſſed the ninth of <hi>July</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, did direct the triall of Sir <hi>John Stowell</hi> by the High Court of Juſtice for Treaſon: And alſo by the aforeſaid Act of the 16th. of <hi>July</hi> 1651. did adjudge his eſtate to be ſold, which Judgement is fully executed by the ſale thereof, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſaid Act. Therefore it ſhall be preſumed, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment did the ſame upon moſt juſt grounds, and the cauſe of their Judgment is not to be examined; Nor is their ſaid Judgement to be reverſed or annulled but by immediate power &amp; authority of Parliament; for all which cauſes the ſaid Truſtees by their Counſell doe demurre in Law, and demand Judgement of the Court, if any further proceedings ſhall be had therein</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Delivered by Maſter <hi>Graves,</hi> 
                        <date>24to. <hi>Nov.</hi> 1652.</date> 
                        <hi> J.W.</hi> 
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Rich. Graves,</hi> Counſel for the ſaid Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>A true Copy.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Tracy Pauncefote</hi> Regiſtr.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Theſe Demurrers were ſolemnly argued before the ſaid Court and overruled, as appeares by this following Order; at the making whereof 26. Commiſſioners were preſent.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="order">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Exchequer Chamber,</hi> Weſtminſter. <date>
                           <hi>Friday the</hi> 31th. <hi>of</hi> December, 1652.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <byline>By the Commiſſioners appointed for Reliefe upon Articles granted in time of War.</byline>
                  <p>UPon large and deliberate debate of the Petition of Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> priſoner in the Tower, wherein he claims the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Articles made upon the ſurrender of <hi>Exeter,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Parliam. contrary to which Articles (as he alledgeth) he hath not onely ſuffered a long Impriſonment, and undergone ſeverall tryals for his life, but Judgments are obtained againſt him to a great value, for things done in time of, and in relation to the late War, and before the date of the ſaid Articles; And his Eſtate ſince ſold by the Truſtees for ſale of Lands forfeited for Treaſon: Whereupon he praies reliefe, having no way (as he ſaith) loſt or forfeited the benefit of the ſaid Articles; unto
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119479:27"/>which Petition ſeverall Pleas and Demurrers have been put in by the Counſell for the Common-wealth, and for the ſaid Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees, the effect whereof is; It appearing that the Parliament hath interpoſed in the caſe of the Petitioner, both in reſpect of his Impriſonment, and in appointing tryals for his life, and the ſelling of his Eſtate, as by them judged to be confiſcated for Treaſon: Therefore to his Impriſonment and poſſeſſion of his Eſtate, it is pleaded, that this Court could not take Cognizance of the Complaint, or examine or give any reliefe thereupon; which Pleas and Demurrers remaining upon record in this Court, with the debates had thereupon: The Court having taken into their ſerious conſideration, and the power and truſt committed to them by the Parliament, in and by their ſeverall Acts for doing Juſtice in caſes of this, and the like nature, after mature deliberation had and taken of the premiſſes, are of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that the ſaid Pleas and Demurrers which for preſent admit the ſtate of the Fact to be ſuch as in the Petition is declared, do not contain in themſelves ſufficient matter to preclude this Court from proceeding in this cauſe, and do therefore reſolve and adjudge that the ſaid Pleas and Demurrers be overruled and ſet aſide. And it is further ordered, that Mr. <hi>Nuttley,</hi> the Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor attending this Court, do acquaint the Councell for the Common-wealth, and the ſaid Truſtees with this reſolution; to the end they may ſet forth ſuch other cauſe as they have to alledge (if there be any on the States behalfe) by way of Plea or anſwer to the ſaid Petition, which the Court holds fit to be done, and delivered into Court by, or before Friday, being the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day of this inſtant <hi>January,</hi> that ſuch further proceedings may be had in the ſaid cauſe, as ſhall appertain to Juſtice.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Tracy Paunceſote, Regiſter.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>IN purſuance of this order the Councell for the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth and for the Truſtees put in their ſeveral anſwers, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo divers of the Purchaſors; and Replications put in by me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: the anſwers of the Common-wealth, the Truſtees, and the ſeverall purchaſors were in theſe words.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:119479:27"/>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="response_to_petition">
               <body>
                  <head>The Anſwer of <hi>Edmund Prideaux</hi> Eſquire, Attorney Generall for the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>England,</hi> to the Petition of Sir <hi>John Stawell.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe ſaid Attorney Generall ſaving and reſerving to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe now and at all times, hereafter all and all manner of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by way of exception, or otherwiſe to the uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, untruths, and inſufficiencies in the ſaid Petition contained, For anſwer thereunto, ſaith, that he the ſaid Attorney Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral knoweth not that the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> was compriſed within the Articles in and by his ſaid Petition mentioned and alledged, to have been made upon the ſurrender of the City of <hi>Exeter,</hi> the eighth day of <hi>Aprill,</hi> in the yeer of our Lord one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred forty and ſix, as in the Petition is ſet forth. Nor that he the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> was in the ſaid City of <hi>Exeter</hi> at the time of ſuch ſurrender thereof, or that he was an Inhabitant within the ſaid City ſeven moneths before the date of the ſaid Articles; and the ſaid Attorney Generall further ſaith, that if in truth he the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> was ſo compriſed within the ſaid Articles, as in and by the ſaid Petition is alledged; yet the ſaid Attorney Generall knoweth not that he the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> did ſubmit unto, or make compoſition for his Eſtate, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the purport and true intent and meaning of the ſaid Articles, and as he ought to have done: with this alſo, that here the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> hath not well and truly performed ſuch of the ſaid Articles as on his part and behalfe were and ought to have been performed, according to the tenor, purport, and true intent and meaning of the ſaid Articles, but hath wilfully bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and infringed the ſame, whereby he hath through his own default forfeited and loſt the benefit of the ſaid Articles. And further, that ſince the time of the ſaid Articles ſo granted as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, he the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> hath been engaged in ſecret Counſels againſt the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and hath done and committed other Acts ſubſequent to the date of the ſaid Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, whereby he hath alſo loſt and forfeited the benefit of the ſaid Articles through his own default, in caſe he was ſo compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed within them, as in and by the ſaid Petition is alledged. And the ſaid Attorney General further ſaith, that by the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawels</hi> own ſhewing in and by his ſaid Petition it doth appeare, and the truth ſo is, that he the ſaid Sir <hi>Io: Stawell</hi> after the making
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119479:28"/>of the ſaid Articles was committed by the Commons of <hi>England</hi> aſſembled in Parliament to the Priſon of <hi>Newgate</hi> during their pleaſure, for high Treaſon in levying war againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And the ſaid Attorney Generall further ſaith (which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo appeareth by the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> own ſhewing in and by his ſaid Petition; that by an Act of this preſent Parliament, paſſed on the ſixteenth day of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1651. the Eſtate of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> by the name of Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> late of <hi>Cudderſton</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet</hi> Knight of the Bath, amongſt divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers was and is declared and adjudged to be by him and them forfeited for his and their Treaſons againſt the Parliament and people of <hi>England,</hi> as by the ſaid Act, relation being thereunto had, appeareth. And the ſaid Attorney Generall further ſaith, that the ſaid Eſtate of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> ſo adjudged for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited, hath been ſince ſold and diſpoſed of in purſuance, and by vertue and Authority of the ſaid Act of Parliament. And the ſaid Attorney General further ſaith, that the Parliament of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> have not hitherto declared their pleaſure as touching the Impriſonment of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> for the Treaſon afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid: And the ſaid Parliament having by the aforeſaid Act, in which all the people of <hi>England</hi> and their conſents thereunto are involued and concluded, adjudged the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to have forfeited his Eſtate for high Treaſon as aforeſaid; and for that the ſame is forfeited, and the ſaid Judgment of Parliament now fully executed; And the ſaid Eſtate of the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> in fact ſold and diſpoſed of, by vertue of, and according to the ſaid Act of Parliament as aforeſaid. The ſaid Attorney Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall further ſaith, that it neither can, nor ought to bee ſuppoſed, that the aforeſaid Judgment is, or hath been given in breach or violation of any Articles confirmed by Parliament, in the obſervation or violation of which Articles, the faith of the Army, and the honour and juſtice of the Engliſh Nation are ſo highly concerned, as by the Petition is ſet forth. Neither hath the Parliament declared what the ſaid Treaſon was, nor when committed, for which they have adjudged him the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> guilty, and his Eſtate to be forfeited as aforeſaid. And the ſaid Attorney Generall neither can, or ought to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to aſcertain the ſame: Neither can this Court bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the ſame without conſulting the Parliament, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till their ſenſe and pleaſure be known therein; without that, that any other matter or thing in the ſaid petition contained, mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall or effectuall in the Law, to be anſwered unto, and not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſufficiently anſwered unto, confeſſed, and avoided, traverſed, or denied is true; all which matters and things the ſaid Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Generall is, and will be ready to aver, juſtifie, maintain, and prove, as this honourable Court ſhall award. And therefore
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119479:28"/>humbly prayeth, that the ſaid Petition may be diſmiſſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Delivered by Maſter <hi>Nutley</hi> 
                        <date>January 28. 1652.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Th. Widdrington.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Edm. Prideaux.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Barth. Hall.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Green.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="response_to_petition">
               <body>
                  <head>The Anſwer of the Truſtees appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Act of Parliament for ſale of Delinquents Eſtates, to the Petition of Sir <hi>John Stawell.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe ſaid Truſtees (ſaving and reſerving to themſelves now and at all times hereafter all and all manner of Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages by way of Exception or otherwiſe, to the uncertainties and Inſufficiences in the ſaid Petition contained, for a clear and full Anſwer to the ſaid Petition) ſay, that by Act of Parliament of the ſixteenth of <hi>July</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred fifty one, The Eſtate of the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> (amongſt others) is therein mentioned to have been, and is thereby declared and adjudged to be juſtly forfeited by him for his Treaſon againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and People of <hi>England.</hi> That by the ſaid Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his Eſtate is veſted and ſettled in the ſaid Truſtees, their Heires and Aſſignes, upon truſt and confidence to ſell and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey the ſame, as in and by the ſaid Act is directed, limited, and appointed. That upon the ſecurity of the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawells</hi> Lands (and other the Traytors Lands by the ſaid Act appointed to be ſold) The ſaid Act doth direct, that the ſumme of two hundred and fifty thouſand pounds ſhould be borrowed for the neceſſary carrying on the ſervice of this Common-wealth. That for the encouragement of ſuch perſons who ſhould be the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſors of the ſaid Lands or any part thereof, It is further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, that they, their Heires and Aſſignes, ſhall have and enjoy the Lands which ſhall by them be ſo purchaſed, diſcharged of all Truſts and accompts whereunto the ſaid Truſtees are or may be lyable by the ſaid Act, and all other claimes and demands what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. That in purſuance of the ſaid Act, and according to the Truſt thereby repoſed in the ſaid Truſtees, They have ſold to ſeverall perſons all Sir <hi>Iohn Stawells</hi> Eſtate: And they are confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and do verily believe, a great part of the purchaſe money is paid, according to the ſaid Act of Parliament to the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119479:29"/>thereby appointed to receive the ſame, and that the ſaid monies have been ſince paid out by the ſaid Treaſurors, as the Parliament and others authorized by them have Ordered the ſame. And therefore the ſaid Truſtees further ſay, That they claime not any manner of Intereſt in the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawells</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, otherwiſe then as perſons intruſted by the ſaid Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as before is declared; Nor do they know, nor doth it concern them to know why the Parliament did enact his Eſtate to be ſold (as aforeſaid.) Wherefore they humbly pray hence to be diſmiſſed.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Richard Graves,</hi> Counſell with the ſaid Truſtees.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>IN humble obedience to an order of the honourable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners appointed by Act of Parliament, for reliefe of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons upon Articles granted in time of War, which Order is dated the ſeven and twentieth of <hi>November,</hi> 1652. and ſerved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſix daies ſince, whereby <hi>Matthew Coker</hi> of <hi>Lincolnes Inne</hi> Gent: is required within 7. daies after ſervice, to make anſwer in writing to the matter of complaint exhibited againſt him, touching breach of Articles by Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> whoſe petition as is informed is now depending before the Commiſſioners afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, according to which the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> deſires to bee releived againſt him concerning a Meſſuage in <hi>Everchreech</hi> and <hi>Preſley</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet.</hi> I therfore the ſaid <hi>Matthew Coker</hi> do for anſwer ſay, that whereas the Truſtees at <hi>Drury</hi> houſe, according to the power given them, had given notice of their reſolutions to make ſale of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawells</hi> Eſtate, and amongſt the reſt of the Mannor of <hi>Preſley,</hi> part of which Mannor being bought by the Town of <hi>Taunton,</hi> and the remaining part which was and is Tennanted by my Brother-in-Law <hi>William Smith</hi> of <hi>Preſly</hi> Gent. being alſo about to be ſold; I therefore at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and requeſt of my owne Brother, and other kindred and friends, and by vertue of an Aſſignment of Tenant-Right from my ſaid Brother-in-Law <hi>William Smith,</hi> became a Purchaſor of all that Right and Eſtate that had been in Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> upon the Land Tenanted by the ſaid <hi>William Smith,</hi> ſome great induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to which Purchaſe, amongſt the reſt was chiefly the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall affection I beare to my Siſter and her Children, who as I had reaſon to ſuſpect might have very much ſuffered, if a ſtranger had bought over their heads; whereupon I confeſſe without the leaſt intimation of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> or any Agent from or under him, I did with the ſaid Truſtees contract for, and buy the ſame; notwithſtanding the Articles of <hi>Exeter,</hi> which I thought would
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119479:29"/>not have concerned me being a private perſon to look into or judge of; and I the rather did the leſſe heed them, having then as I ſtill have an aſſured confidence in the Juſtice of the Parliament, that if at any time they being rightly convinced that the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> ſhould have the benefit of the Articles of <hi>Exeter,</hi> and accordingly admitted him, that care would be taken for giving reaſonable ſatisfaction for my purchaſe-money, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther charges I have been at; and now for that I have made my firſt payment, and have a conveyance from the ſaid Truſtees of the premiſſes ſealed and inrolled, therefore though it ſhall never ſo much appeare that Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> is compriſed in, and ought to have benefit of the ſaid Articles, and be admitted into a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of enjoying the ſame; yet for that I have paid money, and am inveſted as aforeſaid, I think it altogether conſiſtent with the juſtice of the Parliament and the honourable Commiſſioners aforeſaid, firſt to put me in a ſure condition or way of having that reliefe as is proper and neceſſary in a caſe of this nature, before I ſurrender back to the State, or part with any Intereſt I have in the premiſſes: But when I ſhall be aſſured of ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as aforeſaid, I ſhal, being lawfully required, be alwaies ready in obedience to any Parliamentary power to part with my Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt as aforeſaid, which I confeſſe I ſhould have been the more unwilling to have done; but that I have by much experience found, that by reaſon of the doubtfulneſſe whether Sir <hi>Iohn Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> ſhould have benefit by the ſaid Articles or no, doth make for the diſadvantage of the Purchaſor in ſeverall reſpects, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I hope the honourable Commiſſioners aforeſaid will bee gratiouſly pleaſed ſpeedily to decide and put ſome certain peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od to the buſineſſe one way or other.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Wrote and ſigned with my own hand.</dateline>
                     <signed>Matthew Coker.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:119479:30"/>
                  <head>To the Right Honourable the Committee for Articles.</head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>The humble Anſwer of</hi> Iohn VVarr, <hi>and</hi> Iohn Borradale, <hi>Gentlemen, to the Information and Complaint of Sir</hi> Iohn Stawell.</head>
                  <p>THat we did joyntly Contract with the Truſtees appointed by Act of Parliament for ſale of ſeverall Lands and Eſtates forfeited to the Common-wealth for Treaſon of the Demeſnes of <hi>Bewly,</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> being late parcell of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> appointed to be ſold by the ſaid Act.</p>
                  <p>That we were incouraged to the ſaid Contract by the ſaid Act of Parliament; by vertue and authority whereof, we hope and expect to be protected, and to enjoy our ſaid Purchaſe.</p>
                  <p>That how farre the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> is concerned in the pretended breach of the Articles of <hi>Exon,</hi> concernes not us to look at, The Parliament of the Common-wealth of <hi>England</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (as we humbly conceive) ſufficiently weighed and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined the Intereſt of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> in the ſaid Articles, before they expoſed his Land to ſale.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Warr.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Borradale.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:119479:30"/>
                  <head>To the Right Honourable the Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners for reliefe of perſons upon Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of VVarre.</head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>The Anſwer of</hi> Iohn Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well <hi>to the Complaint of Sir</hi> Iohn Stawell, <hi>Knight.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THat he was altogether ignorant of any Articles Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> had; but he Contracted for the Lands mentioned in a Subſcription of Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> to your Honours Order of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the eighth of <hi>December</hi> laſt, with thoſe who (as he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived) had authority to doe the ſame; And ſhall freely ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to what Authority ſhall do therein:</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>By the direction of the ſaid <hi>John Farewell. Delivered</hi> 
                        <date>23. <hi>of February</hi> 1652.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Nicholas Batteley.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſaid</hi> Nicholas Batteley <hi>Anſwers in the ſame words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Edward Buſhell <hi>Anſwers likewiſe in the ſame words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Both delivered</hi> 23. <hi>of February</hi> 1652.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:119479:31"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Honourable the Commiſsioners for releife upon Articles of VVarre.</head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>The Anſwer of</hi> Iohn Gorges <hi>Eſquier to the Complaint of Sir</hi> Iohn Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well <hi>Knight.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THat he was altogether ignorant of any Articles Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> had. But he contracted for the Lands mentioned in a Subſcription of Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> to your Honours Order of Summons of the eighth of <hi>December</hi> laſt, with thoſe who as he conceived had authority to do the ſame, and ſhall freely ſubmit to the like Order for himſelfe, as ſhall be made in the Caſe of other the Purchaſers on Friday next come ſeavenight.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Iohn Gorges.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>I do authoriſe<hi> Thomas Sherwood </hi>Gent. to deliver this as my Anſwer.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Iohn Gorges.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:119479:31"/>
                  <head>The replication of Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> Knight, unto the anſwer of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Prideaux,</hi> Attorney Generall.</head>
                  <p>HE the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> averreth and ſaith all as in his Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition is alleadged and ſaid, and that he was and is a perſon comprized within the Articles in his Petition ſet forth, and at the making of the ſaid Articles and ſurrender of the City of <hi>Exon</hi> in the ſaid City, and ſubmitted unto his compoſition, and did all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things that are requiſite to inable him to the benefit of the ſaid Articles, nor hath broken or infringed the ſame, nor ingaged himſelfe ſince the ſaid Articles in any counſels or Actions againſt the Parliament, nor done other act to forfeit or make him loſe the benefit of the ſaid Articles without that that any other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or things alleadged in the ſaid anſwer of validity to debarre this Petitioner is true, all which he averreth, and prayeth as in his Petition he hath already prayed.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>JOHN STAWELL.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Replications made unto the ſeverall anſwers of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons aboveſaid, are the ſame as is before expreſſed to Mr. Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Generals anſwer, and are omitted for brevities ſake.</p>
            <p>The cauſe being thus at perfect iſſue, witneſſes were appointed to be examined.</p>
            <p>The 24th of <hi>February</hi> 1652. theſe following Reſolves were made in Parliament.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="resolution">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Thurſday, <hi>Febr.</hi> 24. 1652.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>REſolved by the Parliament, That all ſuch perſons as have purchaſed of the Truſtees at</hi> Drury-houſe <hi>the Lands of any Delinquent clay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, or who ſhall claime the benefit of Articles, ſhall hold and enjoy the lands and eſtates ſo by them purchaſed, according to the rules, limitations, and directions contained in the reſpective Acts for ſale, notwithſtanding any ſuch Articles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſolved by the Parliament, That the caſe of Sir</hi> John Stawell, <hi>upon his pretence of Title to Articles be reſumed to the conſideration and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of the Parliament. And that the Commiſſioners for giving reliefe to perſons upon Articles doe forbeare to proceed any further therein untill the Parliament take further Order.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Hen. Scobell, Cler. Parliament.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The late Parliament being diſſolved: The 18 of <hi>May</hi> 1653. I
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119479:32"/>exhibited a Petition to the Commiſſioners for Articles, in theſe words:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Honourable the Commiſſioners for reliefe of perſons upon Articles of Warre.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The humble Petition of Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> Priſoner in the <hi>Tower.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THat your Petitioner is advertized (as by the annexed Letter may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare) of waſte intended to be made upon his eſtate, which if not timely prevented, will very much increaſe thoſe loſſes he hath already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the breach of his Articles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That of late he hath diſcovered the diſpoſure of part of his Eſtate,</hi> viz. <hi>The Prebend and Rectory of</hi> Wilſcombe, <hi>and the impropriate Parſonage of</hi> Halſe, <hi>which are now in the hands of the Committee for plundered Miniſters. And Mr.</hi> Nicholas Bond, <hi>who hath purchaſed the Gleab lands thereunto belonging, to whom none of your former Orders have been dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted for want of ſuch information and helps as might have guided him in this particular.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That by the Interpretation he makes of your late Orders, He humbly conceives leave is given to him to ſollicite this Honourable Court for his reliefe, and that an eſpeciall favour is granted unto him for that purpoſe, of which he is not yet made a partaker.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherefore your Petitioner humbly prayes, that your Order or Injunction may be granted for the ſtopping of waſte, till his cauſe now depending before you receive a determination. That ſuch like Orders may be granted unto the Committee for plundered Miniſters, and to Mr.</hi> Nicholas Bond, <hi>as have been directed to the Truſtees at</hi> Drury-houſe, <hi>and others in the like caſe. And laſtly, that by your favour and leave he may proceed to the examination of Witneſſes, and to the proofe of his petition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>And your petitioner ſhall ever pray, &amp;c.</hi> JOHN STAWELL.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Upon which Petition, the Commiſſioners having heard the Councell for the Commonwealth, and for the Petitioner, this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Order was made.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="order">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>Star-chamber Wiſtminſter. <date>
                           <hi>Wedneſday, June</hi> 9. 1653.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <byline>By the Commiſſioners for reliefe upon Articles of War.</byline>
                  <p>Upon conſideration had of the petition of Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited unto this Court the 18 day of <hi>May</hi> laſt paſt, praying thereby amongſt other things, that he may have leave to proceed to examination of witneſſes, and proofe of his petition; and upon reading the Order of this Court of the firſt of this inſtant
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119479:32"/>
                     <hi>Jane,</hi> whereby it was ordered in the preſence, and at the deſire of the Councell for the Commonwealth, that Councell on both ſides ſhould be heard unto that point this preſent day, Now upon the hearing of Mr. <hi>Maynard,</hi> Mr. <hi>Latch,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Harriſon,</hi> on the behalf of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell:</hi> and of Mr. Attorney Generall, and the Attorney of the Dutchy, for the Commonwealth: And upon conſideration of what hath been offered by either party, and mature deliberation had thereupon, Are of opinion, and doe finde it juſt to order, that the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to proceed in the examination of ſuch witneſſes as have been produced, and are already ſworne in the cauſe, according to the Order of this Court of the ſixteenth day of <hi>February</hi> laſt paſt, and to bring on his cauſe in due courſe to hearing, and do order the ſame accordingly.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>tracy Pauncefote,</hi> Regiſter.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Hereupon Witneſſes were examined by me, to prove my complaint, upon Intergatories, and in their ſeverall depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions did cleerly teſtifie the matters in iſſue which did ariſe out of my ſaid Petition which are too long here to be inſerted yet in reſpect that ſome miſ-repreſentations have been made concerning my deportment and carriage at <hi>Goldſmiths Hall</hi> at the time of the tendering of my Petition for compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, I ſhall make bold for my juſtification againſt thoſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſions to inſert the teſtimony of Sir <hi>Anthony Erby,</hi> and Sir <hi>David Watkins,</hi> two worthy perſons and members of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, and then preſent when I delivered the ſaid Petition, which though it be but a Letter from Sir <hi>Anthony Erby,</hi> yet it relating to his Oath which hee had formerly taken in the Court of Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles to ſpeake his conſcience, and he being a perſon of honour, and free from all exception, I preſume it will gaine that credit which I hope in your judgements will very much cleer me, which followeth in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To my much reſpected friend</hi> Tracy Pauncefote <hi>Eſq. at his houſe in the little</hi> Amory, Weſtminſter.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YOu may remember that ſome time ſince I was ſummoned in by Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>to the commiſſioners for Articles, ſitting in the inner</hi> Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer <hi>chamber as a witneſſe, and was then ſworne but as yet not examined, I have been by ſeverall Letters from Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>requeſted to come up to</hi> London <hi>to be now examined, but the truth is my buſineſſe is ſuch here, having been abſent from my eſtate now above twelve yeares, I cannot come up as he deſireth, upon which he deſireth me to certifie in writing what I can ſay in his buſineſſe, which I am willing to doe, and have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected this Letter to you, that if there be any thing wherein I may doe him Iuſtice, you may make uſe of it at his hearing; I being upon my oath ſhall
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119479:33"/>ſet nothing under my hand but what is truth, which I dare not otherwiſe doe if I were not ſworne. To the firſt I know he delivered in a Petition in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> Goldſmiths Hall, <hi>deſiring to compound for his Eſtate, comming in as I remember upon the Articles of</hi> Exeter, <hi>and I know he delivered his Petition within the time according to the Articles. Some of the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee that were then preſent gave me and the reſt a character of him that he was one of the violenteſt enemies the Parliament then had, That he was one of the very firſt that raiſed Forces against the Parliament, and ſome other ſuch ſpeeches of the diſpoſition and nature of the man; upon which we were reſolved to ſhew him no favour, but found fault that in the firſt place in his Potition he had not acknowledged himſelfe a Delinquent, to which as I remember he anſwered, he came to compound according to his Articles; and deſired the benefit of them. Then we asked him if he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the oath and covenant, or if he had not, we asked him if he would take it; he replyed that by his Articles he was to take no oath; we told him we were commanded that all ſuch as compounded before us ſhould take the oath and covenant, and take the Negative Oath, which he refuſed to doe: we gave him time for eight or ten daies, or a fortnight; I doe not certainly remember, but it was to my certain remembrance, that by that time his time given him by his Articles would be out that we might deale with him the better. For his deportment to us at that time, and the other that he was before us, for my par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> I took no offence at it, neither doe I think juſtly there could be any. He is of himſelfe of a blunt carriage, but for uncivility I ſaw none at the times he was before us, either in geſture or lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. For my part, I would have had him admitted to compoſition, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing money would have done the Parliament ſervice; beſides, by his Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles we ought: but I was but one, others were not of my mind, but height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his offence high, took exceptions at his carriage and language, and would have it reported to the Houſe; for my part, then I thought there was more in it then was outwardly expreſſed: but the truth was, by the order of the Houſe we were bound up from admitting him to compound, unleſſe he took the covenant, except the Houſe would diſpence with it, which they did when they approved of thoſe Articles. But ſince (I muſt confeſſe) I have heard from ſome of the then Members of Parliament, that one of our Society would have bought a Mannor of Sir</hi> John Stawell, <hi>which lay neere him, but I knew nothing of it then, but took notice of ſome tartneſſe in the party, which being neighbours and Countreymen, I ſomething wondred at, thinking that Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>might have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated him by ſome action in the time of war. Sir, if J might know to what the commiſſioners would have me examined, and ſend me the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatories, I ſhall give them as full an anſwer, as if I were preſent. I am confident M.</hi> Leech <hi>muſt ſay the ſame as J doe about the delivery of the Petition, and the reaſons why we then reſpited him, and went not on to his compoſition. Sir J am</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>1 <hi>July</hi> 1653.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your aſſured friend and ſervant, <hi>ANTHO. IRBY.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:119479:33"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>THeſe are to certifie whom it may concern, That I, Sir <hi>David Watkins,</hi> being in the yeere 1646 one of the Committee for compounding with delinquents, then ſitting at <hi>Goldſmiths-hall,</hi> doe well remember that Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> Knight of the Bath came to the ſaid Committee with a faire and civill reſpect, and preſented his petition to them within the time limited by the Articles of <hi>Exeter,</hi> Thereby deſiring that he might compound for his Eſtate according to the ſaid Articles granted to him and others of the Kings party.</p>
                  <p>He had omitted to acknowledge Delinquency in his ſaid Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, neither had he taken the Negative Oath and Covenant, as others in his condition had done before their admittance to compoſition; nor was he willing to ſubmit to either, affirming the ſame to be contrary to the ſaid Articles, and againſt his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to take the Negative oath and covenant. Therefore his Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition was laid aſide, and not received. In witneſſe whereof, I have hereunto, at the requeſt of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> ſubſcribed my name, this third day of <hi>October</hi> in the yeere of our Lord God 1653.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>David Watkins.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Court of Articles were likewiſe pleaſed (the Councell of the Commonwealth conſenting thereunto) to give leave that the whole evidence taken before the High court of Juſtice ſhould be made uſe of at the hearing by either party.</p>
            <p>The Commiſſioners for compounding with Delinquents alſo returned their anſwer to an Order of Court, which followeth in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>By the Commiſſioners for compounding, &amp;c.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>11 <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 1653.</date> Haberdaſhers-Hall, London.</dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IN anſwer to an Order from the Commiſſioners for reliefe of perſons upon Articles granted in time of warre, bearing date the tenth inſtant in the caſe of Sir <hi>John Stdwell,</hi> who claims the Benefit of <hi>Exeter</hi> Articles. We doe hereby ſignifie unto the ſaid Court, that upon ſearch made by our Regiſter, he findes not that there are any papers in his cuſtody which concernes Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> ſave onely an Order of the High Court of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the 26 of <hi>Novrmber</hi> 1650, requiring Mr. <hi>Leech</hi> our late Regiſter to certifie unto that Court the proceedings had in relation to the ſaid Sir <hi>Johns</hi> compoſition; and we are informed that his petition to compound, with ſuch other papers as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned him were there left before the ſaid High court of Juſtice, and not ſithence delivered back to our Regiſter, ſo that we know no further matter againſt the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> then what hath been already ſignified to the ſaid High court upon the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawels</hi> Triall. Here remaines with our Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119479:34"/>ſeverall petitions of the Lady <hi>Stawell,</hi> which we conceive not pertinent to the caſe of the ſaid Sir <hi>John,</hi> and therefore think not fit to trouble the court of Articles therewith.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Sam, Moyer.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Edw. Cary.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Rich. Williams.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ric. Moores.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>T. Bayly.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The 15 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1653. the cauſe came regularly to be heard, and Councell as well on behalfe of the Commonwealth and Truſtees, and of me the petitioner, having been fully heard, and averring they had nothing further to ſay; and in regard none of the Defendants who had anſwered did attend, nor any for them, although Oath was made that they were ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to that purpoſe, the Court took time to adviſe upon the whole matter.</p>
            <p>But in the interim, whilſt the Court was deliberating, and adviſing upon their judgement, the Truſtees of <hi>Drury-houſe,</hi> and the petitioners, to impede the judgement of the Court, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that I had fully proved the ſeverall aſſertions of my petition, whereupon I prayed their reliefe, they preferred two ſeverall petitions to the Committee conſtituted for the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of petitions, which follow in theſe words:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Honourable the Committee for Petitions. The humble Petition and Repreſentation of the Trustees for ſale of lands forfeited for Treaſon.</head>
                  <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                  <p>THat by Act of Parliament, bearing date the ſixteenth of <hi>July</hi> 1651. Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> and other Delinquents therein men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned were adjudged and declared Traytors, and their Eſtates forfeited by them for their ſeverall Treaſons againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and people of <hi>England;</hi> and the ſaid Eſtates were by the ſaid Act veſted and ſetled in us as Truſtees for the ſale thereof to the uſe and benefit of the Commonwealth.</p>
                  <p>And whereas we have according to the truſt repoſed in us, made ſales of the ſaid Eſtates, and thereby raiſed very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſums of money, which have been and are daily diſpoſed of for the Navy and other publique uſes.</p>
                  <p>And whereas divers of the ſaid purchaſers doe come daily unto us with complaints, that they are interrupted by Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> his Agents, in the quiet enjoyment of their Eſtates ſo by them purchaſed, according to the Law.</p>
                  <p>And whereas the late Parliament, upon a petition made unto them by divers of the ſaid purchaſers (a copy whereof is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto annexed) did upon the 24 of <hi>February</hi> laſt make an Order and a Reſolve in the caſe, a copy whereof is hereunto annexed. And
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119479:34"/>notwithſtanding which Order and Reſolve, we are certainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed that the Commiſſioners appointed to give reliefe upon Articles of Warre have ſince proceeded in the caſe of Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> and are ready to give judgement againſt the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
                  <p>We therefore humbly pray your Honours to review the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed petition and vote of Parliament, and that the ſame may he forthwith preſented to the conſideration of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, together with your opinions therein, to doe as ſhall ſeem meet to their grave judgements and wiſdomes, and ſo the honour and credit of Acts of Parliament may be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and the purchaſers ſetled in their undoubted rights; and your petitioners encouraged in the execution of their truſt,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>And your petitioners ſhall pray, &amp;c.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Arthur Samuel.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Samuel Goodkin.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Robinſon.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Skinner.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Liſle.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Houry Sealy.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Mat. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentine.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the ſupream Authority of this Nation, the</hi> PARLIAMENT <hi>of</hi> ENGLAND.</head>
                  <head type="sub">The humble petition of ſeverall Purchaſers of the late Eſtate of Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> on the behalfe of themſelves and other purchaſers of the ſame Eſtate.</head>
                  <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                  <p>THat your petitioners eſteeming Acts of Parliament the higheſt Law, and greateſt ſecurity to rely upon, did purchaſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall parcels of Sir <hi>John Stawels</hi> Eſtate, not imagining any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivative power from you would or could queſtion why you expoſed it to ſale. Notwithſtanding which, your petitioners are daily ſummoned up to ſhew cauſe why Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> ſhould not have his lands, according to Articles of warre. And although the Councell for the Commonwealth on their behalfes have demurred in law, yet is the ſame overruled, and your peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners left in a ſtrange uncertaine undone condition, unleſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved by your juſtice.</p>
                  <p>That your petitioners have incurred great Debts for their reſpective purchaſes, and ſome of them being Tenants have drowned their mean eſtates by purchaſing the Fee; and through their conſtant adhearing to the Parliament, have expoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the mercy of an inveterate implacable enemy.</p>
                  <p>Your petitioners therefore humbly pray your ſpeedy conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the premiſes, and the engagement of your own ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119479:35"/>and juſtice therein, that ſo your petitioners may peaceably enjoy their Eſtates according to their ſeverall purchaſes.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>And they ſhall pray, &amp;c.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Upon which the Committee ordered that Colonel <hi>Rous</hi> ſhould report the ſaid petitions to the houſe; which Order is thus:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="report">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Tueſday, the</hi> 2 <hi>of Auguſt.</hi> 1653.</date> At the Committee for receiving Petitions.</dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>VPon reading the petition of ſeverall purchaſers of the late Eſtate of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> on the behalfe of themſelves and others the purchaſers of the ſame Eſtate. Together with the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition and Repreſentation of the Truſtees for ſale of Lands for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited for Treaſon; and upon ſerious debate and conſideration had thereupon, It is ordered that Colonel <hi>Rous,</hi> who had the chaire of this Committee, doe with all convenient ſpeed report the ſaid petition to the Parliament, and withall offer it as the ſence of this Committee, That the purchaſers ought to have and enjoy their ſeverall purchaſes, according to their ſeverall contracts. And in caſe that Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> ſhall be found within and ought to have the benefit of Articles of war, the Parliament may be pleaſed to give him ſatisfaction, which they humbly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the conſideration of the Houſe.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Report being made, it pleaſed the Parliament to make theſe Reſolves.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="resolution">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Munday, the</hi> 8 <hi>of Auguſt.</hi> 1653.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>COlonel <hi>Rous</hi> reports from the Committee for petitions the humble petition of ſeverall purchaſers of the late Eſtate of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> on the behalfe of themſelves and other purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of the ſame Eſtate, and the ſeverall Votes of Parliament of the 24 of <hi>February</hi> 1652. which were now read.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſolved by the Parliament, That this buſineſſe be taken into conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration on Friday next.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ordered by the Parliament, That it be referred to the Committee for petitions to take care that there be good Councell for the Commonwealth, to attend the commiſſioners for Articles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Hen. Scobell, Cler. Parliament.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>After which Reſolve, <hi>viz.</hi> the 22 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1653. abovementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the Court of Articles did ſolemnly give their judgement, as followeth.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:119479:35"/>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="judgment">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Monday</hi> the 15 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1653. <hi>By the Commiſſioners conſtituted by Act of Parliament for Relief of perſons upon Articles, Conditions and Engagements made in time of War, ſitting in the Exchequer-chamber,</hi> Weſtminſter.</head>
                  <p>WHereas Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> hath exhibited his Petition into this Court, thereby (amongſt other things) ſetting forth, That he is comprized in the Articles made upon the ſurrender of the City and Gariſon of <hi>Exeter,</hi> bearing date the eighth of <hi>April,</hi> 1646. and afterwards confirmed by Parliament: By the the twelfth of which ſaid Articles it was agreed, That no perſon therein comprized ſhould be queſtioned or accountable for any act paſt by them done, or any other done by their procurement, relating unto the un happy Differences betwixt the late King and the Parliament, they ſubmitting themſelves to reaſonable and moderate Compoſition for their Eſtates, which the then General Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> was really to endevor with the Parliament, that it ſhould not exceed two years value of any mans real Eſtate reſpectively, and for perſonal according to the ordinary Rules, not exceeding the proportion aforeſaid: Which Compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being made, they ſhould have Indempnity for their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and enjoy their Eſtates and all other Immunities, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out payment of fifth or twentieth part, or any other Taxes or Impoſitions, except what ſhould hereafter be charged upon them in common with other Subjects, by authority of Parliament. And by the 21 Article it was further agreed, That no Oath, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, Proteſtation, or Subſcription relating thereunto, ſhall be impoſed upon any perſon whatſoever compriſed within the ſaid Articles, but onely ſuch as ſhould binde all perſons aforeſaid, not to bear Arms againſt the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> nor wilfully do any act prejudicial to their affairs, whileſt they remain in their Quarters. That he had a Certificate under the Hand and Seal of the then General, dated the 14 of <hi>April,</hi> 1646. ſignifying, that he was to have the benefit of the ſaid Articles. That the 15 of <hi>July,</hi> 1646. he came to <hi>London</hi> to make his Compoſition, and according to an Order of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſecond of <hi>July,</hi> 1646. and within the time thereby limited undertook by a ſubſcription under his hand, not to bear Arms againſt the Parliament, according to the intention of the ſaid Order and 21 Article. And upon the 24 of the ſame <hi>July,</hi> 1646. he preferred his Petition in perſon to the Committee at <hi>Goldſmiths-Hall</hi> for compounding with Delinquents, deſiring to compound according to the ſaid Articles; But was not admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe he refuſed to take the Negative Oath and Covenant: And was the 13 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1646. for ſuch his refuſal only, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed firſt to <hi>Ely</hi>-Houſe, afterwards by Order of the then Houſe of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119479:36"/>Commons to <hi>Newgate,</hi> for High-Treaſon, in levying War againſt the Parliament, where he continued almoſt four years, and in that time was ſeveral times indicted for Treaſon, and twice ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned for his life at the then Kings Bench Bar: And that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are obtained againſt him in perſonal Actions for ſeven thouſand pounds in Damages; And all this for acts relating to the Differences between the late King and the Parliament, and before the Date of the ſaid Articles. That in <hi>July,</hi> 1650. he was by Order of the High Court of Juſtice removed from <hi>Newgate</hi> to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and there kept in cloſe cuſtody: and the ſeventeenth of <hi>December,</hi> 1650. and divers days after, tryed for his life before the ſaid High Court, who after many days tryal, examination of witneſſes, and ſtrict enquiry into his actions, and the performance of the Articles on his part, did not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to ſentence, but certified their proceedings to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: A copy of which Certificate was annexed to this Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: That ever ſince the ſaid Tryal he was a priſoner, and from the Date of the ſaid Articles his Eſtate ſequeſtred, by which, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his Debts, and felling his Woods and Timber, he hath loſt neer thirty thouſand pounds in his Eſtate, beſides his impriſonment, and hazard of his life. That his Eſtate, by an Act of the 16 of <hi>July,</hi> 1651. is (amongſt others) declared for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited for Treaſon, and hath been ſince ſold accordingly. That neither he, nor his ſons, or ſervants, have engaged againſt the Parliament in any act of hoſtility ſince the ſaid Articles, nor hath he loſt the benefit thereof, by any default of his; and therefore prays, That the ſaid Certificate of the High Court of Juſtice may be conſidered, and the liberty of his perſon, and the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of his Eſtate, may be granted to him, diſcharged of ſuch Judgments, Executions, Sales and incumbrances as are contrary to the meaning of the ſaid Articles, and free from Compoſition, in regard the profits of his Eſtate for ſeven years have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to the uſe of the Commonwealth. Unto which Petition ſeveral Pleas and Demurrers were put in by Mr Attorney Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral on the behalf of the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> and by the Councel for the Truſtees for ſale of Eſtates forfeited for Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, on the behalf of the ſame Truſtees; the effect whereof was, It appearing that the <hi>Parliament</hi> had interpoſed in the caſe of the Petitioner, both in reſpect of his impriſonment, and in appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tryals for his life, and the ſelling of his Eſtate, as by them ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged to be confiſcated for Treaſon; Therefore that as to his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, and poſſeſſion of his Eſtate, the Court could not take cognizance of the complaint, or examine or give any relief there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, as by the ſaid Pleas and Demurrers, reference thereto being had, may more at large appear: Which Petition, Pleas, and Demurrers coming regularly to hearing before this Court, after long debate and mature deliberation had of and upon the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119479:36"/>ſame; this Court, upon the 31 of <hi>December</hi> laſt paſt, declared their opinion. That the ſaid Pleas and Demurrers (which for the preſent admitted the ſtate of the Fact to be ſuch as is ſet forth in the ſaid Petition) did not contain in themſelves ſufficient matter to preclude this Court from proceeding upon the ſaid Petition; and did therefore reſolve and adjudge the ſame to be over-ruled and ſet aſide: and appointed the Solicitor for the State, attending the Court, to acquaint the Councel for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and the ſaid Truſtees with this Reſolution, to the end they might ſet forth ſuch other cauſe as they had to alledge (if there were any) on the States behalf, by way of Plea or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the ſaid Petition: And the Court alſo, at the prayer of the Petitioner, iſſued forth ſummons to ſuch perſons as were by the Petitioner named Defendants, and certified by the Truſtees aforeſaid to have been Purchaſers of the Lands and Eſtate of the Petitioner, to plead or anſwer to the Complaint of the ſaid Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner. Hereupon the Councel for the Commonwealth put in an Anſwer, wherein they ſay, they know not that the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner was comprized in Articles, nor that he was in the City of <hi>Exeter</hi> at the ſurrender, nor an Inhabitant there ſeven Months before the ſaid Articles: and that if he were comprized, he knew not that the ſaid Petitioner did ſubmit unto, or make Compoſition for his Eſtate, according to the true meaning of the ſaid Articles, and as he ought to have done: and avers, that the Petitioner had not performed ſuch of the ſaid Articles as on his part were to be performed, but had wilfully broken and infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the ſame. That he hath been engaged in ſecret counſels ſince the ſaid Articles, againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and committed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther acts ſince the Articles, whereby he hath forfeited the benefit of the ſame Articles through his own default: And by way of Anſwer, further alſo ſets forth the ſame matters of Law former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſiſted upon in his ſaid Plea and Demurrer, whereupon this Court had formerly delivered their Judgments as aforeſaid. The ſaid Truſtees alſo put in their Anſwer, and ſay, That by the ſaid Act of the 16 of <hi>July,</hi> 1651. the Petitioners Eſtate was ſetled in them upon Truſt, to convey the ſame as the ſaid Act directed: and that in purſuance thereof they have ſold to ſeveral perſons all the ſaid Eſtate, and do believe that a great part of the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe Mony is payd; and claim no other intereſt in the ſaid Eſtate, then as perſons intruſted as aforeſaid; neither know, nor are concerned, why the <hi>Parliament</hi> have enacted the Petitioners Eſtate to be ſold. Several perſons, named Defendants by the ſaid Petitioner, did alſo appear, and put in Anſwers to the ſaid Petition: In particular <hi>Matthew Coker</hi> of <hi>Lincolns</hi> Inn, Gent. ſaith. That he hath purchaſed from the ſaid Truſtees part of the Manor of <hi>Prieſtley,</hi> being parcel of the Lands of the ſaid Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner, and hopes to have back his mony and charges before he
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119479:37"/>ſurrender: and then he ſays he ſhall be always ready to do the ſame. <hi>John War</hi> and <hi>Iohn Borradale</hi> ſay, That they have joyntly contracted with the ſaid Truſtees for the Demeaſnes of <hi>Bewley</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> part of the Eſtate of the ſaid Petitioner. That how far the Petitioner is concerned in the pretended breach of the Articles of <hi>Exon,</hi> concerns not them to look at; the <hi>Parliament</hi> having, as they conceive, ſufficiently weighed and determined the intereſt of the ſaid Petitioner in the ſaid Articles before they expoſed his Lands to ſale. <hi>Nicholas Batteley, Iohn Farwell, Edward Buſhell,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Gorges,</hi> by their ſeveral Anſwers ſeverally ſay, That they have contracted for the Lands reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively mentioned in the ſubſcription of the Petitioner to the Order of this Court of ſummons of the eighth of <hi>December</hi> laſt, with thoſe who they conceive had authority to do the ſame; and each of them freely offers to ſubmit to what authority ſhall do therein. Unto which Anſwers of the Councel for the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and the ſaid Truſtees, and of the ſaid other Defendants, the Petitioner Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> replyed, averring the truth of his ſaid Petition: and the cauſe being at perfect iſſue, witneſſes were examined, and their Depoſitions publiſhed, and by the conſent both of Mr Attorney General, and of the Councel for the Petitioner, the whole evidence taken before the late High Court of Juſtice, upon the Tryal of the ſaid Petitioner before them, was agreed to be made uſe of by either party at the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the cauſe. The Court having alſo received the Anſwer of the preſent Commiſſioners for compounding, &amp;c. ſitting at <hi>Habberdaſhers</hi>-Hall, <hi>London,</hi> certifying, That they have no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matter againſt the Petitioner, then what hath been already ſignified to the ſaid High Court upon his Tryal, by vertue of their Order in that behalf; did appoint this day for the hearing of the whole cauſe. Now upon full hearing of Mr <hi>Latch,</hi> Mr <hi>Harriſen,</hi> and Mr <hi>Amhurſt,</hi> on the behalf of the ſaid Petitioner, and of Mr Attorney General, Mr Attorney <hi>Hall,</hi> and Mr <hi>Hurſt,</hi> on behalf of the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> together with Mr <hi>Graves</hi> on the behalf of the ſaid Truſtees; and upon reading of the ſaid An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers of the ſaid other Defendants, purchaſers of part of the Petitioners ſaid Eſtate, they, nor any of them appearing, nor any for them, although due notice had been given unto each of them of the time appointed for the hearing of this cauſe (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Oath is made) the Court proceeded therein: and upon the hearing of the evidences and witneſſes, produced on the behalf of the ſaid Petitioner and of the Commonwealth, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration had of what ſtands admitted and proved before this Court; they do finde, and are clearly of opinion, That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> is within the Articles of <hi>Exeter</hi> confirmed by <hi>Parliament;</hi> by which no perſons therein comprized, and ſubmitting to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Compoſition for their Eſtates, are to be accountable or
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119479:37"/>queſtioned for any act paſt by them done, relating unto the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Differences between the late King and the <hi>Parliament.</hi> That the Petitioner perſonally appeared before the Committee of the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and ſubſcribed according to an Order in <hi>Parliament</hi> of the ſecond of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1646. not to bear Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> nor wilfully do any act prejudicial to their affairs, whileſt he remained in their Quarters: which we finde to be agreeable to the 21 of the ſaid Articles. That he alſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally appeared the 24 of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1646. being within four months after the ſaid Articles, and preſented a Petition to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of <hi>Goldſmiths-Hall</hi> for Compoſitions, mentioning therein his Eſtate to be ſequeſtred, and humbly praying they would pleaſe to admit him to Compoſition, according to the ſaid Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and the then Generals Certificate, rendering him capable of that agreement; but his ſaid Petition was rejected. That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell's</hi> tender of that Petition in the manner proved before this Court, was a ſubmiſſion to Compoſition according to the ſaid Articles of <hi>Exeter.</hi> That he was afterwards by Warrant of the ſaid Committee of the 13 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1646. committed to <hi>Ely.</hi> Houſe, for refuſing to take the Negative Oath and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, enjoyned by the Ordinances of <hi>Parliament</hi> of the fifth of <hi>April,</hi> 1645. and firſt of <hi>November,</hi> 1645. That ſince that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment he hath been continued priſoner in ſeveral Goals, and during that reſtraint hath been ſeveral times indicted and brought in queſtion for his life, for acts relating to the unhappy Differences, ſuppoſed by him to be done before the granting of the ſaid Articles. That it appeareth not to this Court, that he hath by any act or default of his loſt or forfeited the benefit of his ſaid Articles, which we finde to be approved by the then Houſe of Commons the ſixth of <hi>May,</hi> 1646. and by both Houſes of <hi>Parliament</hi> the fourth of <hi>November,</hi> 1647. who ordered that Approbation of theirs to be publiſhed, and all Committees, Judges, Officers, and other perſons concerned, to take notice thereof, and obſerve the ſame, any Orders or Ordinances to the contrary notwithſtanding. That ſince his ſaid ſubmitting to compound, the profits received forth of his Eſtate being ever ſince until the late ſale under Sequeſtration, and the Damages thereby by him ſuſtained appear to amount to above 25000 <hi>l.</hi> That by the Truſtees Anſwer in this caſe, it appears they have ſold all his Eſtate, by reaſon of the Act for ſale, wherein he is included: And the Defendants, <hi>Matthew Coker, John Warr, John Borradale, Edward Buſhell, John Farwell, Nicholas Batteley,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Gorges,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge they have bought of them the ſaid Truſtees ſeveral parcels of the ſaid Eſtate. That the ſaid Petitioner Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> being tryed for his life before the late High Court of Juſtice ſitting in the years 1650, and 1651. that Court finding him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſaid Articles, and that he had ſubmitted to Compoſition,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119479:38"/>thought not fit to proceed to ſentence, but to certifie his Caſe to the <hi>Parliament:</hi> Upon which Articles this Court finds not any Judgment to be ſince given; but diſcern themſelves impowered, authorized, and required by <hi>Parliament,</hi> to give relief to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons wronged through breach of Articles, in ſuch ſort as is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the Acts made in that behalf. All which this Court having taken into their ſerious conſideration, and how far the Faith of the <hi>Army,</hi> and Honor and Juſtice of the <hi>Parliament</hi> and Nation are concerned in this, and the like caſes, That right be done, and no violation of Articles permitted, after many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates and mature deliberation had thereupon; and being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in their judgments and conſciences, that the Petitioner Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> is fully capable of the Relief intended to perſons within Articles, by the Acts directing and authorizing the ſame, and conſtituting this Court; Do in order thereto, and in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of the power and truſt to them committed in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, <hi>Reſolve, Declare, and Adjudge,</hi> That the Petitioner Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> hath good right, and by his ſaid Articles ought to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to compound for his whole Eſtate, real and perſonal, according to the tenor of the ſame Articles, notwithſtanding any the Settlements, Sales, or Contracts before-mentioned, at ſuch rates, and in ſuch manner, as others comprized within the ſaid Articles have done: and the Commiſſioners for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding with Delinquents, are hereby enabled, authorized, and required, to permit the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to compound for his whole Eſtate, as aforeſaid: And in reſpect of thoſe great Loſſes and extreme Damages which the ſaid Petitioner hath ſuſtained by the Sequeſtration and Detention of his Eſtate, and the profits received out of the ſame for above ſeven years laſt paſt, and by the felling of his Woods and Timber, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, for want of being admitted to a timely Compoſition; This Court doth order and direct, That the ſaid Commiſſioners for compounding do cauſe an exact account to be made of the Rents, Iſſues, and profits, received for, or out of the Petitioners Eſtate, ſince he firſt ſubmitted to Compoſition, and was not admitted thereunto: and do recommend to their conſideration the proofs thereof already taken in this cauſe, Copies whereof, atteſted by the Regiſter of this Court, are for that purpoſe to be preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them: And if the ſaid Commiſſioners ſhall finde the ſame to amount unto, or exceed the Fine or Compoſition which the ſaid Petitioner ought to pay, according to the rates preſcribed, and allowed by the ſaid Articles of <hi>Exeter,</hi> That then the ſame be allowed, accepted, and taken in lieu and full ſatisfaction of ſuch Fine or Compoſition ſo impoſed upon, or to be ſatisfied by the ſaid Petitioner Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> according to his Articles; otherwiſe the defect (if any happen to be) is to be ſupplyed by him the ſaid Petitioner: and if any ſurpluſage or overplus
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119479:38"/>remain, the ſaid Commiſſioners for compounding are hereby ordred and deſired to certifie the ſame unto this Court. And upon ſuch computation, &amp; ſatisfaction made as aforeſaid, the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners are hereby directed and authorized to give their Order for ſuch acceptance of the Petitioners Fine and Compoſition, and to give the Petitioner a Diſcharge accordingly: and they are deſired to give him all fitting expedition in the premiſſes. And it is further ordered, adjudged, and declared by this Court, That after the making of the ſaid Compoſition as aforeſaid, the ſaid Petitioner Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> ſhall have the Liberty and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnity of his perſon free from any further reſtraint or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, according to the true meaning of his ſaid Articles: and that all Bayl, or other ſecurity, entred into by the ſaid Petitioner, or any other perſons with or for him, touching his true Impriſonment, be thereupon delivered up to the ſaid Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner, and vacated and diſcharged: and that he be in the mean time permitted, upon the Bayl already by him given, to proſecute and attend the perfecting of his ſaid Compoſition without let or moleſtation. And that the ſaid Petitioner Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> from and after ſuch Compoſition as aforeſaid, ſhall have the poſſeſſion of his Eſtate, freed and diſcharged from all Sequeſtrations and Seizures whatſoever, and ſhall enjoy the ſame without any claim, demand, impediment or moleſtation of the ſaid Truſtees, or of the Survivors and Survivor of them, their or any of their heirs. And this Court doth further award, order, and judge, That the Truſtees for Sale of Lands and Eſtates forfeited to the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> for Treaſon, do upon ſight of this Order and Award, ſtay and forbear all further proceedings in the Sale or Diſpoſal of any the Land and Eſtate of the ſaid Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> remaining unſold (if any ſuch be:) and if any part of the Monies remain unpayd, for any Lands belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Petitioner already contracted for and ſold, that they likewiſe forbear to demand or receive the ſame, or to make any further proceedings touching the ſame, or intermeddle any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther therewith. And it appearing unto this Court, by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers of the ſaid ſeveral Defendants, <hi>Matthew Coker, Iohn Warr, Iohn Borradale, Nicholas Batteley, Iohn Farwell, Edward Buſhell,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Gorges,</hi> that they have contracted for, and purchaſed ſome parts and parcels of the Petitioners Lands and Eſtate, menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned and referred to, in and by the Anſwers afore mentioned, the detention whereof is to the prejudice, and tending to the diſheriſon of the ſaid Petitioner, and contrary to his ſaid Articles; This Court do order and adjudge, That from and after the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of the Compoſition aforeſaid, and notice given thereof, and of this Order and Judgment, the ſaid <hi>Matth. Coker, Iohn Warr, Iohn Borradale, Nicholas Batteley, Iohn Farwell, Edward Buſhell,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Gorges,</hi> do forthwith reſtore unto the ſaid Petitioner Sir <hi>Iohn
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119479:39"/>Stawell,</hi> and his heirs, the full and peaceable poſſeſſion of all and every the premiſſes by them purchaſed, as aforeſaid: And that after the making of the ſaid Compoſition, the ſaid Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner, and his heirs, ſhall and may peaceably and quietly hold and enjoy the ſame Hereditaments, with their and every of their members and appurtenances, freed and diſcharged of and from all claims, charges, and incumbrances, in any wiſe occaſioned by or under them the ſaid Defendants, purchaſers reſpectively. And the ſaid Truſtees, and the Survivors or Survivor of them, or any of them, their, or any of their heirs, or any perſon or perſons, claiming by, from, or under them, or any of them, in as free and ample manner, as if the ſaid laſt mentioned premiſſes had not been ſequeſtred, or veſted, or ſetled in the ſaid Truſtees and Purchaſers, or any of them; and as if no ſuch Settlements, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts, or Sales, had been had or made. And the ſaid Truſtees at <hi>Drury</hi>-Houſe, and alſo the ſaid <hi>Matthew Coker, John Warr, Iohn Borradale, Nicholas Batteley, Iohn Farwell, Edward Buſhel,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Gorges,</hi> and every of them, and all others, who are or may be any way herein concerned, are upon notice hereof, to give their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance hereunto accordingly. And it is laſtly Ordered and Declared, That the Petitioners bringing the preſent Cauſe to hearing againſt the aforenamed Defendants, ſhal be no bar to him to proceed further upon his ſaid Petition againſt other Defendants already named, or who ſhall be hereafter made Defendants to the ſaid Petition; but that he may proſecute ſuch perſons upon the ground of his ſaid Complaint, ſo far as he ſhall ſee occaſion, and be adviſed: And upon the ſame Petition, if cauſe be, bring thoſe cauſes alſo to Iſſue and Judgment, in order to his juſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief; The now Award and Judgment given in this Cauſe, or any other matter or thing herein contained to the contrary, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Jo. Bradſhaw</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Edw. Whalley</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Edward Cook</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>William Boſvile</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Anth. Samwell</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Owen Rowe</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>John Hayes</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Clem. Oxenbridge.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:119479:39"/>
            <p>This Judgment being given and declared by the honourable Court of Articles, after they had ten moneths moſt judiciouſly ordered and directed the proceedings in the cauſe, to the end that there might be left no ſcruple in any Intereſt unſatisfied, Mr. At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torney Generall and the reſt of the Counſell for the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and the Counſell for the Truſtees being heard at large, I did not conceive but that all ſuch who were concerned would have reſted in it. But after all this I finde the endeavours of the Truſtees and ſeverall Purchaſers of my Eſtate do tend directly to render my proceedings for the gaining of my right unſuccesfull; for upon the 29th. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> ſeven daies after this Judgment, the Parliament reſumed the debate of the Purchaſors Petition and Repreſentation of the Truſtees, and did reſolve as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="resolution">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Monday the 29th.</hi> Auguſt, 1653.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe houſe took up the former debate upon the Petition of the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſers of the Eſtate of Sir</hi> John Stawell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The humble Petition and Repreſentation of the Truſtees, for ſale of Lands and Eſtates forfeited to the Common-wealth for Treaſon was this day read.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Reſolved</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Parliament, that this Petition of the Purchaſers of Sir Iohn Stawells Eſtate be referred back to the ſame Committee, to conſider what is fit to be done for the reliefe of the Petitioners, and report to the houſe withall ſpeed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Henry Scobell,</hi> Clerk of the Parliament.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Hereupon Mr. <hi>Pauncefote</hi> the Regiſter of the Court of Articles was commanded to attend the ſaid Committee with the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that Court, together with the ſeverall Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment conſtituting that Court, and all the pleadings and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings which had paſſed in my Cauſe.</p>
            <p>UPon which reference of the Houſe to the Committee, to conſider what was fit to be done for the reliefe of the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſers, it ſeemes they have thought fit to report, that the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſers of my Eſtate ought to enjoy it; And upon that report you have been pleaſed to make this Reſolve.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="resolution">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Tueſday the 15th. of <hi>September,</hi> 1653.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Reſolved,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THat this Houſe doth agree with this Report of the Committee, that the Purchaſers of Sir</hi> John Stawells <hi>Estate ſhall quietly poſſeſſe and enjoy the ſame, according to their ſeverall Contracts made with the Trustees.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Henry Scobell, Clerk of the Parliament.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>From this it may appeare that the <hi>Committee</hi> for receiving of <hi>Petitions</hi> not purſuing (as I humbly conceive) the intention of the order of <hi>Reference</hi> which did refer to their conſiderations, (after I had the Judgment of the Court of Articles for part of my Eſtate) what was fit to be done for the reliefe of the <hi>Petitioners,</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:119479:40"/>they did reſume the matter which formerly they had offered, and inſtead of propoſing a way how the Purchaſers ſhould be <hi>relieved,</hi> it was reported as a thing agreeable to their <hi>Iudgments,</hi> that their Eſtates ſhould be confirmed; upon report of which as their ſenſe and opinion, it hath pleaſed the Parliament to make the laſt mentioned <hi>Reſolve.</hi> This being ſhortly my caſe, and ſurely my ruine, if by your favour not prevented, I beſeech you in the next place to conſider what <hi>power</hi> you have <hi>reſerved</hi> unto your ſelves, by the expreſſe words of the Act of ſale of the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>July,</hi> 1651. <hi>fol.</hi> 1373. and how the Truſtees ſtand limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the execution of their Truſt; the words are theſe. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs upon truſt and confidence that the ſaid</hi> William Skinner <hi>and others the perſons above named, or any five or more of them ſhal have, hold, and enjoy, all and ſingular the Premiſſes, and every of them</hi> (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Lands and Eſtates of the perſons in the Act named of which I am one) <hi>ſubject unto ſuch truſts and uſes as by this Act, or in and by Authority of Parliament ſhall be hereafter further directed and appointed, and ſhall diſpoſe of the ſame accordingly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſon of this <hi>Clauſe</hi> and <hi>Limitation,</hi> I humbly conceive to be, for that the Parliament having confirmed and ratified divers <hi>Articles</hi> and <hi>Conditions</hi> granted in time of war, to the making good of which, their <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Justice</hi> as well as the <hi>faith</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> and <hi>Nation</hi> was eminently concerned, and for that at the time when this Act did paſſe they neither did nor could poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly take notice of ſuch as had right or claim to the ſame, they reſerved unto themſelves this power, and did provide that the Truſtees ſhould order and diſpoſe of the ſame accordingly.</p>
            <p>And by their Act of the 29th. of <hi>September,</hi> 1652. for reviving of the Act of the 18th. of <hi>June,</hi> 1649. which upon juſt and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable grounds gave reliefe <hi>to all ſuch perſons who are or ſhall bee arrested, ſued, impleaded, impriſoned, or ſequestred, contrary to any Articles given or granted, &amp;c.</hi> a Court for that purpoſe being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted to do right in all the particulars of both the ſaid Acts, according to the tenor and meaning of Articles, any Law, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or Ordinance to the contrary notwithſtanding: By which Act and Declaration the Parliament doth make uſe of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer power, expreſly reſerved unto them. And if any mans eſtate or part thereof be ſold contrary to the Right of Articles, it is no wrong unto the Purchaſers, if it be by Judgement reſtored to the right Owner; for the Decree or Judgment that ſhall ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore it, is given by Authority of Parliament, and is in order to the Power in the Act of ſale reſerved unto the Parliament ſo to do.</p>
            <p>And the Purchaſers have no cauſe to complain (ſo as recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence be aſſigned unto them) for that their bargaines and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts made with them could not be abſolute and direct, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119479:40"/>the ſaid clauſe of Limitation had debarred the Truſtees themſelves, from whom they clayme in the caſe of Articles, from any ſuch abſolute eſtate: And therefore it ſeemes, that ſome of them taking notice of this reſerved power, upon paſſing the Act of Revivour, preferred the two Proviſoes afore-mentioned to the Parliament. That that Act which was then to paſſe, ſhould not extend, or be conſtrued to extend to prejudice, alter, or make void any Reſolution, Vote or Judgement given in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment touching any the Articles aforeſaid, or any perſon claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby. As alſo that no Reall or Perſonall Eſtate, which hath been ſettled, conveyed, or aſſured to any perſon or perſons by vertue of any Act, Order or Ordinance of the then Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhould be made null, vacated, or otherwiſe determined or diſpoſed of by the Commiſſioners named in that Act, or by their Authority, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But the Parliament, reflecting upon their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the caſe of Articles, upon the queſtion rejected both the Proviſoes. And whereas if they had been approved, I had been ruin'd and undone; ſo by the ſame reaſon, being rejected, I may with the help of your favour and juſtice, be preſerved and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to what is properly and of right belonging unto me.</p>
            <p>Thus in all humbleneſs I have Remonſtrated and faithfully declared unto you to the beſt of my remembrance by what meanes I came to take up Armes in the behalf of the late KING in thoſe moſt unhappy diſtractions (my Judgment at that time being ſatisfied of the KINGS reall intentions and unfeigned con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy thereunto, for the ſure eſtabliſhment of Religion, and the Lawes, the ſafety and wellfare of the People, as alſo to declare how, and in what manner I proceeded during all the time of my ſervice and imployment, And upon what Termes, Articles, and Conceſſions I ceaſed from further action on the KINGS Part, and that by thoſe Articles I was to have had my perſon freed and unmoleſted, and my Eſtate reſtored upon a moderate Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which now at length by your Judgment (as is aforeſaid) and Decrees grounded upon your Lawes and Acts of Parliament are awarded unto mee. And I am very confident that had it not been for the ill Offices of ſome particular perſons begot by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned prejudicie, and nurſed by the heat of their paſſions againſt me, I ſhould long ago have been ſet at liberty from a tedious Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, and have been in the actuall poſſeſſion of my Eſtate by the Juſtice of the late Parliament, to whom I cannot impute any Injuſtice, or report any thing that is diſhonourable. But ſince they were but men, and by the neceſſity of their humanity they were enforced to take reports from others of ſuch matters as were Acted at a diſtance from them, and perhaps by ſuch (though altogether unknown to them) as might ſo preſent things as their private intereſt might lead them, by which means my Right hath been much retarded; ſo in like manner I make
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119479:41"/>it no queſtion, that when you who are their Honourable Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors ſhall be truly informed of the ſtate of my condition, having caſt your cies upon this Narrative, where you may perceive up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the whole deduction, that notwithſtanding the utmoſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and diſquiſition that either the malice or intereſt of my Adverſaries could promote and project againſt me for my ruine and deſtruction, I have had the Judgement and reſolution of two great and honourable Courts; the one for the ſafety of my life, and the other for the reſtitution of my eſtate; which Judgments, conſidering the ability and integrity of the perſons, &amp; gravity &amp; equanimity of their proceedings in their pleadings, debates, and conſultations, I hope are fully ſatisfactory; And the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the reſult of them is but the affording of me that Juſtice which is ſo eminently grounded upon that indiſputable law of Nature, without which the foundation of no government what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever can be ſure or laſting, the law of Contracts being recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally the obligation of protection from the ſupreme Power and ſubjection in the People who ought to obey, and that aſwell in military as civil Order; which the noble Army taking into their ſerious conſideration, have made it by publick Petition to the late Parliament of <hi>Aug.</hi> 12.1652. one of the weighty Clauſes of their requeſts, <hi>viz. That the Articles of War made unto the Enemy may be made good, according to the intent of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Petition by Order of the Councell of Warre was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by ſix honorable Officers of the Army, and had a very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable and gracious Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as there doth not appeare by any proof a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me (though no ſtone hath been left unturned under which any thing might be found for that purpoſe) that I am in the leaſt guilty of any Act tending to the non-performance of all ſuch things as on my part I was bound unto by the ſaid Articles, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the time of the rendition of the ſaid city of <hi>Exeter,</hi> nor that I have acted any thing ſince contrary to my ſubſcription made at <hi>Guild</hi>-Hall; I do make it my humble ſute, that the Juſtice and Honour of the Parliament and Nation, and the Faith of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my may be made good unto mee in reſtoring of me to the benefit of my Articles, the afore-mentioned Judgement, and ſuch fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther right and Juſtice, as is extended unto me by the ſeverall Acts of Parliament eſtabliſhed for my relief.</p>
            <p>And as it is my humble and frequent prayer to that great God, who hath for many yeares miraculouſly fed me, to beſtow upon me my dayly bread; ſo let it not I beſeech you be a thing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing unto you, if I pray (in a time when neither Eſtate or Credit is left me) for ſo timely a conſideration hereof as may ſtand with the reſt of your weighty affaires.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Stawell.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
